<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reuniting of Christianity, or, The manner how to rejoin all Christians under one sole confession of faith written in French by a learned Protestant divine ; and now Englished by P.A., Gent.</title>
            <author>Learned Protestant divine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 138 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17163072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17163072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1099:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reuniting of Christianity, or, The manner how to rejoin all Christians under one sole confession of faith written in French by a learned Protestant divine ; and now Englished by P.A., Gent.</title>
                  <author>Learned Protestant divine.</author>
                  <author>P. A., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 235, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Winter for William Gilbert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union.</term>
               <term>Christian sects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REUNITING OF Chriſtianity. OR The Manner how to rejoin all Chriſtians under one ſole Confeſſion of Faith.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>French</hi> by a Learned Proteſtant Divine, And now Engliſhed by <hi>P. A.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>John Winter,</hi> for <hi>William Gilbert,</hi> at the <hi>Half Moon</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:2"/>
            <head>THE AUTHORS PREFACE</head>
            <p>IF it be a great cauſe of grief to all true Chriſtians, to ſee the ſacred Religion, which the Son of God brought down from Heaven to the Earth, miſerably torn in pieces by ſo many ſeveral Sects, which heretofore have, and who ſtill divide it at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: If all theſe different Confeſſions of Faith, which diſmember the ſpouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, do extraordinarily afflict all pious Souls; ſurely theſe pious Souls ſhould conceive no leſs grief at this, that hitherto there has never been any that has undertaken to apply a healing remedy to theſe wounds, that has attempted,
<pb facs="tcp:106061:3"/>with ſucceſs, the cure of ſo great an evil. It ſeems no more to be thought of, but as an evil to be deplored, and abſolutely incurable. Every one thinks himſelf ſtraightly bound to ſtick to his old prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and preconceived opinions: every one flatters himſelf in his own thoughts, and believes, that he poſſeſſes the Truth. and is in the right way; after which he looks no more upon others but with ſome kind of averſion; or, at leaſt, with pity, They, in the judgment of him and his party, are as ſo many unfortunate crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ready to tumble down an unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable precipice: they are conſidered as people that are only ſit to be the ſubject of the prayers which are offer'd up for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretches, or of the complaints w<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               </hi> are formed againſt their unhappineſs. Neither are thoſe looked upon who would undertake to remedy this, but as idle Projectors and fantaſtical perſons, like Mountebanks, who promiſe the Cure of thoſe Diſeaſes that are given over by the moſt skilful Phyſicians.</p>
            <p>I know very well, that many have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed to find out a means of according
<pb facs="tcp:106061:3"/>ſome of theſe Sects, to reunite certain perſons together, who have been engag'd in them, and who, on this account, have reciprocally entertained moſt implacable feuds againſt each other. There have been divers Writings publiſhed for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring an accommodation between the Roman Catholicks &amp; Proteſtants: they have attempted to reconcile thoſe of the Confeſſion of <hi>Ausburg,</hi> vulgarly ſtiled Lutherans, with thoſe other called Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts; but there have commonly been other intereſts than thoſe of the Glory of God, intermixed in theſe enterpriſes. It has rather been by a principle of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy than by any motive of Conſcience, and deſire of the ſalvation of Souls, that theſe deſigns have been ſet on foot: whence it has happened, that God has turned his Bleſſing from them, and made the ſucceſs not to anſwer the greatneſs of the deſign. Some likewiſe, not aiming at any thing herein more than how they might make ane aſier paſſage, &amp; more plauſible revolt, from one Communion to another, have only ſtudied to weaken the foundation of their former opinions, and ſtrengthen
<pb facs="tcp:106061:4"/>that of their new ones, which they have an intention to embrace. There is alſo this in it, that men do not ordinarily attempt, but to remedy ſome effects, without aſcending up to the principal cauſe, and only ſource of all this evil; juſt like thoſe ignorant Phyſicians, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfully labour to cure ſome of the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of Diſeaſes, without applying any thing to the grand original Cauſe, on the curing whereof depends all its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences.</p>
            <p>There was a Preface of a Book, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome years ſince, in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, which touched this matter, and ſeemed to aim at a general reconciliation of all Chriſtians, by means of a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table allowance and and a mutual tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But beſides that, it was but by the by, that the Author treated upon this important Subject: It ſeems that, not having aſcended up to the ſpring head of all theſe Diviſions, he has not contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any proper way, for the Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation which he propoſes, nor has rightly diſtinguiſhed between what is fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in Chriſtian Religion and what is
<pb facs="tcp:106061:4"/>not, to let us ſee, laſt of all, in what things we ſhould have this charity one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another. And we reject alſo the means which is moſt important to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the attaining to ſo good an end, whilſt we refuſe to diſingage our ſelves from whatſoever may render it unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as I ſhall ſhew you in its proper place.</p>
            <p>It was in the ſearch of this, that I have, for ſome years ſince, applyed my ſelf to ſo diligent and ſerious meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I utterly caſt off, at the inſtant, all former opinions of my own, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt others, which might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obſtacle to me in ſo laudable a deſign: I diſingaged my ſelf for a time of all things whatſoever of any Communion of Chriſtians, which was ſingular, and which ſeparated it ſelf from others: And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that in examining carefully the things wherein they all agreed, I might diſcern with a more diſintereſted eye, that which would be for the common good. I then conſidered with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt exactneſs that I was able, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Greatneſs, and lamentable Effects,
<pb facs="tcp:106061:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106061:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106061:6"/>of this miſerable Diviſion of Chriſtians. I obſerved at the ſame time, how ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable would all thoſe goods and all thoſe advantages be, which would ariſe from their reuniting into one &amp; the ſame Confeſſion of Faith, and reconciliation of their minds into the ſame Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. After that, I diligently conſidered with an intire applying my mind, what could be the cauſes of ſo deplorable a misfortune: I have aſcended the beſt I could to the very fountain head of this evil, where, I ſuppoſe, I have made ſome diſcoveries, which, without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will be reliſhed by thoſe who ſhall look upon them without intereſt. In ſhort I am verily perſuaded, that after all my endeavours, nay continual prayers have been heard by the Goodneſs and Bounty of the <hi>God of Peace:</hi> I hope, that through the Bleſſing of Heaven, I have met with the true and only remedy of this evil, that is to ſay, the ſole means of reconciling together all thoſe who make profeſſion of Chriſtianity, and who are perſwaded, that the Doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, which is compriſed in the Scriptures
<pb facs="tcp:106061:6"/>of the New Teſtament, is delivered to us from God, and that it contains what we ſhould know, believe and do for our ſalvation. So that as ſoon as we ſhall religiouſly reunite, in thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which it preſcribes to us, we ſhall be in a ready way of attaining to the mark which it propoſes to us. At leaſt, I may, with truth, ſay, that ſince that very time, I have found, for my own part, a great calmneſs of Spirit. I have not any more, ſince that, looked upon Chriſtian Doctrine, to be difficult, knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, charged and encumbred with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of ſubtil queſtions, critical and unprofitable notions. Theſe are the very things, that have made it to paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, having utterly disfigured its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Beauty: This is it, that has given it a face altogether new and ſtrange; and, I dare ſay, that if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles ſhould deſcend down, this very day, upon the earth, they would not know this Doctrine, ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed as it is. And this ſame alſo is it, that has cauſed theſe miſerable Diviſions among Chriſtians, at this preſent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:7"/>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that I, for a great while, had a deſign, not to publiſh my thoughts upon this Subject. I would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed this advantage, which I had met with, and made it of particular uſe to my ſelf. It was not for any envy that I bare to the publick good, for which I could be glad to employ all my power and life: But I have always diſtruſted my own abilities, and knowing, as I do, their utmoſt, I have ever been ſuſpicious of their productions. Beſides this, I did never approve of that liberty which is given of expoſing openly all our thoughts to publick view, or to ſay more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all thoſe whimſies which we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in our Studies. It is to do a great prejudice to men of Learning, to ſteal from them the time which is ſo dear to them. It is ſtaying them to pick out good from bad Writings, that is, to ſearch for ſome grains of Gold amongſt heaps of Sand. It is to buſie the Preſs about fruitleſs Works, which ought not to be employed but in the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: It is, laſtly, to entertain the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the vulgar, who are not able to
<pb facs="tcp:106061:7"/>make diſtinction of Books, and who, many times, being drawn by a ſpecious Title, are afterwards obſerved to be deeplier engaged in ignorance and error.</p>
            <p>Moreover I know that the opinions of the publick are very tenderly to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, for every one will ordinarily paſs verdict upon other mens Works, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſway of their own paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Whence it often comes to paſs, that perverſe Judgments are made on the moſt innocent deſigns. I fancied, that ſome would ſay of me, that I was but in jeſt, to make ſport, that others would imagine, that I acted herein by ſome of thoſe motives which I had already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and condemned; and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny alſo of thoſe who did not abſolutely diſapprove of my thought, might ſay, that it is a thing rather to be deſired than hoped for, that the execution is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and that therefore all the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts would be without ſucceſs. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I ignorant how curious this age is. That now a days much ſeaſoning is required to the choiceſt meats; and that if the moſt excellent ſubjects be not
<pb facs="tcp:106061:8"/>accompanied with a ſtudious and elegant ſtile, they diſcourage the Readers, and are thrown aſide, as merchandiſe not worth looking on. And it will be a hard matter for me, at above ſixty years of age, to contrive a ſtile that ſhall carry with it that air and neatneſs, which ſhall pleaſe the refined Wits of our times. But after all, I thought that I ought not to quit a deſign ſo profitable and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant to the publick good, for ſome objections of ſmall conſequence; that the matter ought more to be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than the Form. I conſidered that Diamonds ſhould not be thrown away becauſe they are rough; and that the golden Oar has always its value, although it hath not yet attained to the luſter which the Cruſible gives it, when its pure body ſhall be ſeparated from the droſs and earth which ſoyl it. The leaſt articulate and weakeſt voices are kindly heard, when employed to adviſe us of our good, and to conduct us out of ſome unſafe courſe. And perchance it may ſo fall out, that ſome or other of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of this age, excited by my weak
<pb facs="tcp:106061:8"/>endeavours may worthily accompliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what I have but rudely eſſayed: and thus it often happens, that the unskilful play of ſome indifferent Muſician ſtirrs up thoſe who have a more delicate touch to correct the defects of the former by the excellency of their hands. All theſe conſiderations, after ſundry debates, did induce me to upbraid my ſelf in terms not much unlike the poor Leppers of <hi>Samaria,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings, ch.</hi> 7. Theſe wretches having met with great riches and a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of proviſions in the Camp, which the <hi>Syrians</hi> had left behind them, blamed themſelves for keeping cloſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a good which might relieve the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of all the inhabitants of their City. I have therefore, at laſt, taken my Pen in hand to communicate to the Publick, the fruit of a Meditation, to which I have applyed my ſelf for a long time.</p>
            <p>I have endeavoured in this little work to follow a familiar method accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to the humours of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; wherein my principal aim is to make all Chriſtians, even the moſt weak
<pb facs="tcp:106061:9"/>and ignorant, comprehend the nature of that Religion which they profeſs, by bringing it back to its firſt principles &amp; fundam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tal Doctrines: But to attain to this end, it muſt be repreſented in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dreſs, by clearing it from whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may render it obſcure, ridiculous and barbarous. I do ſtrive to make my ſelf underſtood by all the world and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion any thoughts and expreſſions to the capacity of every one. To which effect I have divided this ſmall Treatiſe into three principal parts: in the firſt I ſhall let you ſee the Nature, the Extent, and ſad Conſequences of this lamentable Diviſion, which is among Chriſtians; The greatneſs of the Evil ſhould make us know how urgent and preſſing is the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of its remedy. The ſecond will diſcover the Cauſe of the Evil, by laying them open even to their very ſource head. And laſtly, the third will ſet forth the ſoveraign and infallible remedy which may be employed for the curing and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this grievous wound.</p>
            <p>If I perceive that this work is ſeriouſly entertained, and that it ſhall produce any
<pb facs="tcp:106061:9"/>good fruit, I will bleſs God for it with all my heart, ſince it is only his Glory that I propoſe for the ſole object of my deſign. And I will further beſeech him to beſtow on me ſo much health and ſtrength, that I may be able to make this Treatiſe be followed by two others, which wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be of no leſs importance: one of which ſhall be concerning the Counſels which Chriſtian Princes and States may take to make this enterpriſe ſucceed aright, by preſerving their true and lawful intereſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thoſe of private perſons. The other ſhall be to diſpoſe all thoſe who are out of the Pale of Chriſtianity, utterly to caſt away from them all thoſe prejudices which blindly retain them in their ancient Religions, and hinder them from ſeeing the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of that which the Eternal Son of God has given us: ſo that they ſhall ſee how nature it ſelf, and reaſon, does pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully invite them to ſubmit to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, by a perfect obedience; and that it is the only means to enjoy a real tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of mind, and a ſolid quiet in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. This will ſufficiently ſerve to
<pb facs="tcp:106061:10"/>excite Chriſtians (after their reunion ſhall be procured) to contribute on their parts towards the Salvation of all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the world, with whom they ſhall entertain any commerce.</p>
            <p>And as there is nothing ſo repugnant to the deſign which I have in hand as the prejudices wherewith it may be looke upon: for they are theſe prejudices which have ſo much fomented and ſtrengthened this Diviſion, and which would alſo be capable to deſtroy the fruit that might be hoped for from this project<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So I have, on this occaſion, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ured as much as in me lay, not to give the leaſt hint that ſhould ſeem to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour any prejudice whatſoever. I have avoided, as a dangerous rock, giving the leaſt ſuſpicion that I am intereſted for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny party; and content my ſelf, without taxing any one in particular, to blame in general whatſoever hath cauſed theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and whatſoever entertains them at preſent. 'Tis for this reaſon, that I have not been ſpurred on to this deſign by any motive of Vanity, as to acquire the glory of having undertaken an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe
<pb facs="tcp:106061:10"/>which never any man propoſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and likewiſe to take away all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts which my Profeſſion or my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition might give: For I know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that if the Proteſtants did believe that this project had been contrived by a Roman Catholick, and eſpecially by a Clergy man of that Religion, they would think partially on it, and that it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready engaged by intereſt to favour thoſe of their Communion: and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if the Roman Catholicks were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that it was the work of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, or of a Greek, they would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately reject it. And, without doubt, the averſion that they have to thoſe whom they pretend are out of the Church, would make them refuſe the moſt ſaving remedies, becauſe it would be preſented them by a ſuſpected hand: it is juſt as a ſick perſon takes not, but with great fear, any Medicine which is ordered him by a Phyſician whom he miſtruſts. The ſame might be ſaid of all other Communions, which are found amongſt Chriſtians, they look upon one another with ſo much Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and Suſpicion, that only the very
<pb facs="tcp:106061:11"/>thought that ſo laudable a deſign had been laid by a perſon who was not of their Communion, would be ſufficient to make them reject it without any further examination.</p>
            <p>But to draw to a concluſion, I doubt not but that ſome coming to conſider the nature of the remedy which I propoſe, for the cure of this evil, ſhall eſteem it but as a thing eaſie to conceive: that they will ſay, this Idea was no more than what any man might have thought on: that it is a project which, at the firſt, is very ſpecious, and which finds no great difficulties at a ſlight conſideration of it, but which will meet with ſuch as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquerable, if any one undertakes to ſet it on foot. But beſides the great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage it is to have a means of fancying ſuch an Idea as is accompanyed by that of peace and concord, the only names of which are capable of exciting an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of joy in the hearts of all men; I hope ſo to unmask this deſign, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſuch a face, that all ſhall underſtand the foundation, the poſſibility and great advantage thereof. For I pretend not
<pb facs="tcp:106061:11"/>to put an end to this great work, without anſwering to the principal objections, which may be made againſt it. And I do promiſe (as I have ſaid before) another Treatiſe, wherein, in caſe this ſhall be favourably received, I will propoſe a means how to make this project ſucceed: I ſhall let you ſee how the power and authority of thoſe muſt be employed, who are in a capacity of working ſucceſsfully in it. And I beſeech God to ſend down his bleſſing hereupon, and guide all to his Glory, to the good of his Church, and to the comfort of all thoſe good Souls, who ſhall ſigh after ſo holy a Reunion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:12"/>
            <q>
               <p>ET nunc miror maxime, &amp; uſque antehac miratus ſum, eo pleroſque Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos eſſe ingenio, ut inter ſe concordiam colere non poſſint: quod mihi in monſtri loco, eſſe videtur. Cum enim eam reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem ſectentur, qua nihil un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam fuit, nec unquam erit, aut ſanctius, aut ſimplicius, aut ad humanitatem accommodatum magis, illi tamen inter ſe ita vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vunt, ut tigres, urſos, panthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, leoneſque, ac rabioſos canes in unam caveam concluſos di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas. Hincque adeo faclum, ut jamdiu mihi ſit perſuaſiſſimum,
<pb facs="tcp:106061:12"/>qui ita ſunt, eos nihil minus eſſe quam Chriſtianos, etiamſi tales ſe haberi poſtulent. Neque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim internecinis odiis, turpiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis opprobriis, ac atrociſſimis calumniis, ferro deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ac flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, ut fit, alii adverſus alios graſſarentur, &amp; amorem Dei, ac proximi charitatem viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: queis ſublatis nihil aliud fuerit Chriſtianiſmus quam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men inane, &amp; vana aliqua ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, quae contemplantis otium oblectet. Id apud me cum nuper, ut ſaepe alias, non ſine graviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma indignatione dolorem, opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to allatus iſt hic libellus ſine omni ſcriptoris nomine; in quo tantam utilitatem reperi, ut, ſi
<pb facs="tcp:106061:13"/>quod tam diuturno ac pene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medicabili malo adhiberi reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium poſſit, id illius ope eventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſſe arbitrer. Eum certe ita probavi, ut repentino mentis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctu percuſſus, meum de illo judicium his verſibus incluſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, non ſine votis, ut te, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, Chriſtianum eſse bona ſide oſtendas. Et ſiet, ſpero. ubi ſcriptoris mentem &amp; conſilium pernoveris.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Marc. IX.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:106061:13"/>
               <l>DEſcende ſummis,</l>
               <l>Pax alma, polis,</l>
               <l>Celereſque per aethera purum</l>
               <l>Extende pennas,</l>
               <l>Frondenti nitidum caput</l>
               <l>Impediens olivâ.</l>
               <l>Jam ſatis, O nimium ſatis,</l>
               <l>Te juga Olympi,</l>
               <l>Et Long a exilia,</l>
               <l>Et dirae ſcelerum facies, ac triſtia bella Averſam tenuere.</l>
               <l>Aude itaquo oblitas nunc, Diva, reviſere terras,</l>
               <l>Chriſtiadumque genus genus irritabile, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</l>
               <l>Concordes illis mittens per pectora ſenſus.</l>
               <l>Laeta redi, Virgo, tecum unà Aſtraea redibit,</l>
               <l>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lliaque inter ſe traducent otia gentes</l>
               <l>Diſſidiis odiiſque procul. Te turba Ache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rontis,</l>
               <l>Te bellona tremet venientem, &amp; magnus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſdem</l>
               <l>Sub te, ſacra canens, Orbis venerabitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</l>
               <l>Fia age, jam cernes divelſa abrepta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</l>

               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:106061:14"/>Et corpus lacerum in ſedes rediiſse priores:</l>
               <l>Donique jam Chriſto redivivum reddere Chriſtum,</l>
               <l>Et ſecura potes: Nam lato limite, fertur</l>
               <l>Hic liber, averſoſque animos tibi, Sancta, reducit,</l>
               <l>Per populos jam juradabis; Te quiſque ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemus,</l>
               <l>Et tua tam denſis ſtabunt altaria donis,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t te rellicts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>encant oblivia Coeli,</l>
               <l>Et dubites poſthac <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um ſecula laeta videbis,</l>
               <l>Sideribus Terrae praeſtent, an ſidera Terris.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:14"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Firſt Part.</hi> Of the Diviſion which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians, and of its Conſequences.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>CHAP. I. <hi>OF the nature and greatneſs of this Diviſion. Page</hi> 1</item>
                  <item>CHAP. II. The firſt Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>Diſquiet of mind, and trouble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. p.</hi> 15</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:106061:15"/>
CHAP. III. The Second Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>That it destroys the study of Holineſs, and eſpecially the practice of charity.</hi> 26</item>
                  <item>CHAP. IV. The Third Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>That it makes men irreligious, and cauſes Atheiſm.</hi> 35</item>
                  <item>CHAP. V. The Fourth Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>That it keeps back all thoſe who are without, and breeds in them a diſlike of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> 44</item>
                  <item>CHAP. VI. The Fifth Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>Trouble in Church and State.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:106061:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Second Part.</hi> Of the Cauſes of this Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>CHAP. I. <hi>THat the frame and temper of mens Minds doth much contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to this evil. p.</hi> 69</item>
                  <item>CHAP. II. <hi>That there has never yet been made a true distinction in Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, of what is really eſſential and fundamental and what is not.</hi> 80</item>
                  <item>CHAP. III. <hi>That men have departed from the true fundamentals of Chriſtian Religion, to take up others which have nothing of ſolidity in them, and which put theſe diviſions among Chriſtians.</hi> 88</item>
                  <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>That the diſlike which has been had at
<pb facs="tcp:106061:16"/>the ſimplicity of Chriſtian Religion, has been an occaſion, that me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> have given it a different <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ct fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m that which it had in its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>inning.</hi> 97</item>
                  <item>CHAP. V. <hi>That many do make uſe of Religion, to ſerve their particular intereſts, and the advantages of a temporal life.</hi> 106</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Third Part.</hi> Of the proper means to reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all Chriſtians into one ſole communion.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the ill means that has been made uſe of hitherto, for putting a remedy to the evil of this Diviſion.</hi> 117</item>
                  <item>CHAP. II. The firſt mean. <hi>To lay aſide all prejudices, and to
<pb facs="tcp:106061:16"/>throw off all particular intereſts, that ſo nothing may be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by us, but the Glory of God and the Salvation of Souls.</hi> 128</item>
                  <item>CHAP. III. The ſecond means. <hi>That we ſhould not have for our dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, more than one known and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally approved Rule for all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to walk by.</hi> 142</item>
                  <item>CHAP. III. The third means. <hi>Rightly to distinguiſh between the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which the Holy Scriptures propound to be believed by all true Chriſtians, and what regards only the outward Government of the Church and its ceremonies.</hi> 150</item>
                  <item>CHAP. V. The fourth means. <hi>To diſtinguiſh between that which the Scriptures propoſes to us to believe, as Doctrine of Salvation; that which it delivers to us, as Hiſtories of things which have happened; and
<pb facs="tcp:106061:17"/>that which it reports to us as predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of things to come.</hi> 163</item>
                  <item>CHAP. VI. Fifth Advice. <hi>Touching the Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, which we muſt believe, as being revealed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and concerning the diſtinction which muſt be made of them.</hi> 170</item>
                  <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>What ways muſt be follow'd to facilitate the execution of this deſign.</hi> 186</item>
                  <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Anſwers to the Objections, and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties which may be formed against this deſign.</hi> 199</item>
                  <item>CONCLUSION. <hi>Profits and advantages which might be hoped for from this Project.</hi> 218</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:17"/>
            <head>THE <hi>RE-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITING</hi> OF CHRISTIANITY.</head>
            <head>The Firſt Part. <hi>Of the Diviſion which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians, and of its Conſequencies.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Nature and Greatneſs of this Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>That it was neceſsary there ſhould be Hereſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, to the end that ſuch as are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106061:18"/>approved might be made manifeſt.</hi> His words muſt not be taken, as if he would by an extravagant Paradox Authorize the diverſity of Opinions in Chriſtianity. For his deſign was never to favour the Authors of Sects and Heads of Patties, by impoſing ſilence to thoſe who would remedy Diviſions, and put a ſtop to their ſad conſequencies. But he declares plainly, what we muſt expect from the ill diſpoſition of the ſpirits of Men, from the high eſteem which they have of their own ſufficiency, and from their inclination to render themſelves conſiderable, by ſome ſingular Opinions in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. He deſigns by the ſame means to make us ſee how the providence of God, which draws good out of evil, and light out of the thickeſt darkneſs, takes occaſion from thence, to diſtinguiſh ſuch as appeartain to him: making appear by this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106061:18"/>of ſinners, the conſtancy of the Servants of God, and their generous reſiſtance to all ſorts of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations and tryals. It is in this ſence alſo, that <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> declares to us the neceſſity of ſcandals and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ariſing <hi>in the Church;</hi> and that he is come to kindle the Fire-brand of War in the World, and to put Diviſions in States and Families, for otherwiſe the Goſpel, which is the Miniſtry of Grace, and a Word of Reconciliation and Peace, does not of it ſelf propoſe any thing, but uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, amity and concord. Nature, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſprung from the ſame Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal with Grace, hath inclinations quite diſtinct: It is not pleaſed, but in diverſity, and ſeems not to ſubſiſt but by the contrariety of qualities, which occur in its works; whereas Grace is not preſerved, but by the entire correſpondence of thoſe who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve a ſhare therein, and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106061:19"/>of their Opinions. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not divide our ſelves in its Principles without deſtroying it to us. For ſuch a ſeparation is to give it ſuch grievous wounds, as will force it to retire from thoſe who are not more careful to improve it by ſuch wayes as are moſt ſuitable to its nature.</p>
               <p>Now, is it not a moſt deplorable thing, that an occaſion ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of making uſe of a Doctrine of Peace, for the miſerable tearing in pieces a Body, whoſe Members ought to be perfectly united? Is it not a ſhameful thing that this unhappy <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> ſhould be introduced to make the ſame havock in the <hi>Church</hi> which it ordinarily makes in the World? Philoſophy never ſaw ſo many Sects: <hi>Paganiſme</hi> ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Devotions. <hi>Mahometiſme</hi> ſo many contradictory Opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their <hi>Alcoran,</hi> as we have Sects, Hereſies and Schiſmes in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106061:19"/>about the underſtanding of its fundamental Law, which is the Goſpel. As ſoon as the ſprouts of this Holy Seed began to appear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the Earth, we ſaw at the ſame time an infinite number of unprofitable and choaking Tares ſpring up, ſufficient to deſtroy that in its birth, which would bring with it Salvation and Life. Almoſt in the ſight of the Holy Apoſtles, (thoſe Sacred Confidents of our Soveraign Maſter) there aroſe ſuch as vaunting themſelves to have embraced his Doctrine, would have repreſented him after their fancies, and ſet him forth as their own whimſies and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prichioes ſuggeſted to them. And preſently afterwards would make their particular Sentiments paſs for general and infallible Rules, and have pretended that all others were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſubmit themſelves thereto. Thus the Blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106061:20"/>ſtill reeking, ſhould warm the hearts of Chriſtians, with a Holy Charity, as well as with an Ardent Zeal, could not choak the Seeds of theſe miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Diviſions. Inſomuch that in the Third Age, St. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers up Four-ſcore ſeveral Hereſies, (or rather different Opinions) which had crept in amongſt the Chriſtians, and yet not mentioning the divers Branches into which theſe Hereſies were ſub divided. There is ſcarcely any one Article of Faith, or any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation of Chriſtianity, whereon ſtrange Opinions have not been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, which in time have made Sects, and different Religions. And we know that every particular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination has appropriated to it ſelf the Name of a Church, and boaſted to be the Spouſe of the Son of God, to the utter excluſion of all others. They have alſo gone further, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Heavenly Doctrine contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106061:20"/>in the Goſpel, where they have taken occaſion of raiſing diſputes; They have forged ſuch as have been meerly humane, concerning which there hath alſo been miſerable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions. And as though theſe Men had climbed up to Heaven to conſult the very Mouth of God himſelf, they have Preached up their Doctrines as Oracles, and Fundamental Truths. After which they have had no great trouble to engage their Followers to ſuffer the moſt cruel Torments, and even Death it ſelf in defence of their Opinion, and after that have confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently enrolled them in their own Legend, as Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt, though they ſuffered only to advance the glory and reputation of ſome Arch-Heretique. So God to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtize the raſhneſs and confound the vanity of their thoughts, has permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that Diviſion ſhould ruine their work, as heretofore it defeated the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106061:21"/>inſolent deſigns of thoſe who would erect the Tower of <hi>Babel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After that we have once forſaken the Royal Road, which God has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed us, we run into all by paths, and ſeparate our ſelves one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, each of us fancying to be in the moſt commodious and ſafeſt way. Can you likewiſe believe that a ſeparation is ſometimes made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Subjects, not only light and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial, but in ſome ſort ridiculous, and which do redound to the ſhame of thoſe who made them ſerviceable to the ends of their Schiſme and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion? What contentions have there not been among Chriſtians, namely, on what Day the Celebration of <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> ſhould be obſerved; If, in the Communion, Bread leavened or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened ſhould be made uſe of; If the Body of Jeſus Chriſt was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible after its conception, or not; If we may ſay that one of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106061:21"/>was Crucified: If the Church can condemn, and excommunicate one that is dead. If the Hallelujah might be Sung in <hi>Lent,</hi> and other Queſtions of the like nature? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here what are ordinarily the ſubjects, which cauſe theſe moſt real calamities. Behold that which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates thoſe; who with one conſent ſhould advance the glory of their common Maſter.</p>
               <p>But to come to our times, and more neerly to touch upon the evil which troubles us at preſent, and which has given me occaſion of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open my ſence, to contribute to a Remedy: Is it not a lamentable thing, and of ſad Example, to ſee Chriſtians ſo miſerably divided, as they are at this Day? For, to let paſs the divers Sects of Chriſtians, which are in the Eaſt, and who have more cauſe to grieve for their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Diviſions, than for their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106061:22"/>miſerable ſtate, under the rigorous Yoke of the <hi>Mahometans;</hi> ſuch are the Greeks of <hi>Armenia</hi> and <hi>Circaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> the <hi>Neſtorians, Jacobites, Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, Cophtes,</hi> Chriſtians of St. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> &amp;c. People who are looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Hereticks or Schiſmaticks, and who believe that out of their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular communion, there is no Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be expected; Let us inſiſt only upon this deplorable condition of the Chriſtians of Europe in theſe Countreys wherein we live. There is no heart ſo hard that does not ſigh to behold ſo ſtrange a diſ-union; There is no truly Chriſtian Soul, that does not grieve to ſee the effects of the implacable ſudes and hatreds, which are amongſt thoſe who are looked upon as Brethren; <hi>Since</hi> they are thereby expoſed to the continual inſolencies of the ſworn Enemies of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Since this great breach which is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106061:22"/>made in the Weſtern Church, by the ſeparation of the Proteſtants, from the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> what Bloody Wars! How many Murders and Maſſacres! What changes and ſubverſions is in States! has there not been ſeen, inſomuch that they have not ſtuck to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the common Enemy to draw in ſuccour againſt thoſe with whom they ſhould have entertain'd a true Brotherly affection? And that which is moſt deplorable is, that this diviſion hath been followed by an infinite company of others, and as a fruitful Mother hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced an incredible number of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which reſemble it. Theſe two great Branches growing out one from the other, have alſo ſprouting out of them, a vaſt company of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Branches, which although not equal in ſtrength, bring forth fruits altogether as dangerous as their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106061:23"/>Among Proteſtants, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeveral Sects in <hi>Germany,</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> There needs but ſome diverſity in the habits of Preachers, ſome difference in the Ceremonies, or in the Ornaments of Churches, or of the Government thereof, to form a Sect. A ſimple diſſenting in the Liberty which every one gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of expounding according to his Fancy, the miſteries which are above his reach, is ſufficient to cauſe a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. The manner of explaining the ſubject of Predeſtination, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reconciling God's Grace with the Motions of the Will of Man, makes us look upon thoſe who are of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Opinion, as ſuch People as are in the high-way of Damnation, and with whom we muſt not enterta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> any Communion.</p>
               <p>Nor may they who have lived in Communion with the Church of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106061:23"/>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> inſult at this Diviſion of the Proteſtants, and pretend that union and concord have continued amongſt them without any diviſion; For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they all ſubmit themſelves in appearance to the Authority of one only Head, and that they look upon him as the Center, wherein all the Lines of their Society do meet and are reunited, nevertheleſs we are not ignorant, how great the number of their diſſentions are, and how little the union is amongſt their Doctors. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that if the fear of a Superior Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſeems to retain them in one and the ſame Society, their hatreds are but the more fermented within. They do not leſs condemn one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Hereſie, and of being out of the way of Salvation. And the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mples of our Age have ſhown us, that when oppertunities have been preſented, of making their averſions appear, how far they have carried it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106061:24"/>being always deſirous that their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Opinions might prevail over all others. Therefore it is not any particular intereſt that I here endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to advance; But, it is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral intereſt of all Chriſtian Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; It is the good and the union of all thoſe who march under the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the Croſs. I deſign to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite together all the Chriſtians of the Eaſt and Weſt, <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> Catholicks and Proteſtants, and all the divers Branches where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into theſe latter are ſubdivided.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106061:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. The firſt Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>Diſquiet of Mind and Trouble of Conſcience.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WEre there no other Evil in this Diviſion, than the very Diviſion it ſelf, and that deformity which it cauſes in Chriſtian Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Were there no other harm done by it, than the disfiguring the Face of Chriſtianity, and the blem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing its beauty that renders it ſo conſiderable, it would be ſo great a cauſe of grief, as to oblige us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, with all our power, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy ſo great a miſchief. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, this unhappy Diviſion is very fruitful, and produces infinite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106061:25"/>evils, as much or more pernicious than it ſelf. 'Tis like the Viper, which by a ſtrange ſelf dilaceration, makes a great Number of little Serpents come out of her, which inſtantly make their Teeth and Venom appear. There are ſome who ſet upon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, and others who cauſe great diſorders in Societies, both ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and Eccleſiaſtical, as I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to make evident, to every one.</p>
               <p>The firſt effect of this Diviſion, is diſquiet and torment of mind, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ordinarily do plunge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who are engaged in this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berinth of divers Opinions, about matters of Religion; And <hi>theſe</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions do in time forme the different Sects and Societies which divide all Chriſtians. A Traveller Journeys with pleaſure, ſo long as his way ſeems good and plain, and that he is aſſured it is the right, that it lies di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106061:25"/>and finds it is not divided into other different Paths; But ſo ſoon as he perceives himſelf in a croſs Road, where he meets with ſeveral tracks, without knowing which of them he ſhould make choice of; 'Tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but that being in this ſuſpence, he muſt have a great unquietneſs and grief of ſpirit. If all Chriſtians per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly agreed in Opinion, that Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be a grand means wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we might advance with pleaſure towards our happineſs; But meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this great diverſity of ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and profeſſions, wherein every one boaſts of poſſeſſing the truth, as by birth-right to the excluſion of all others; we muſt needs be involved in great perplexity. For to think that we can eaſily ſolve doubts, by a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſerious applying of our minds to meditation, and by the force of <hi>reaſoning and diſcourſe, is a Fallacy,</hi> for beſides that every one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106061:26"/>hath cauſe of diſtruſting himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt this great diverſity of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Seeing that the cleareſt Wits, the moſt profound Doctors, <hi>Men of the choiceſt Endowments,</hi> and ſuch as have the greateſt Piety, ſweetneſs &amp; Moderation of Temper, are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times obſerv'd to be ſeparated and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, the one from the other; I am aſſured that many oft times in theſe applications, how zealous ſoever, nay even after the moſt fervent Prayers, be overſwayed by the probability of the Arguments, which every Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath produced in its own favour. And I durſt ſay that when one has ſo ſoon determin'd in this ſcrutiny, there may be ſome reaſon to ſuſpect ſo quick a reſolution: I am apt to fear that this may often reſpect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intereſts, than thoſe of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and our Salvation, which could ſo quickly make us bend to them. It many times happens that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106061:26"/>our Education, our Cuſtomes, our particular advantages, and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſiderations, do eaſily turn the Scales. And that indeed which abuſeth us herein, is, that theſe are ſlipt in ſo dexterouſly, and mixed in ſuch a manner in theſe diſputations, that we cannot diſcover them, but by ſtrong and frequent reflections.</p>
               <p>But let us put the caſe, that a Man who has an extraordinary light, by the knowledge of Tongues, and read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Good Books, may wade through theſe difficulties, and ſowe his doubts among theſe perplexities. What ſhall we ſay of ſo many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Perſons, who have not had, nor ever been in a Condition to have, all theſe ſo profitable helps, I mean, ſo neceſſary for the penetrating into theſe profound miſteries, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them through that Labyrinth? Is it becauſe that Chriſtian Religion is not propos'd, but only to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106061:27"/>Is it not as well addreſſed to the Ignorant, to Women, to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to the poor unlearned Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants? Muſt we not rather ſay, that it is towards ſuch that it turns the moſt Favourable Aſpect? That whilſt the Doctors are diſputing with great earneſtneſs together, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Myſteries of the Kingdome of Heaven, the moſt ſimple do for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly take it by the ardour of their Zeal. Therefore what can we point out more contrary to the Peace and Conſolation of theſe good and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Souls, than this great diverſity of Opinions, of Sects, and of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions?</p>
               <p>But, if it ſhould be objected, that for want of reading and neceſſary ſtudy to ſearch, into the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime myſteries of Religion, theſe ordinary People would be content with what is moſt plain and moſt clear in Chriſtian Doctrine, which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106061:27"/>will ſuffice to inſpire them with the Love of Virtue, and the fear of God; and that will be capable to give them peace of Conſcience, and all inward Conſolation, that is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for them. I ſhall readily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that this is all I demand, and to which I endeavour to reduce all Chriſtians in general. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Religion is equally propoſed to all, and in the diſtribution of its Graces, it makes no diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Learned and the Ignorant: The High-towering Wit, and that which creeps among the Vulgar: As the Remedies and Medicines which Nature offers us, work in the ſame manner upon Perſons of all conditions and degrees. So that to be a Man, ſuffices to qualify us for laying claim to the advantages which Grace preſents to Us in the Doctrin of the Goſpel, and to lay hold of the Aids which it gives us,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106061:28"/>to make Us partakers of it.</p>
               <p>But ſhould it be likewiſe object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the clearing this difficult Point, that thoſe who have not the means and advantage of penetrating into theſe ſecrets, by a deep medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may conſult the Learned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them, in the choice which they ſhould make of a good and ſure O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion; Who does not ſee, in the firſt place, that it is not the way to draw them out of the trouble, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are, ſeeing they do not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs themſelves, but to Men who are not infallible, and who may be prepoſſeſſed with prejudices, and have their particular Intereſts, ſo that they ſhall be always in doubt, whither or no the advice which was given them, proceeded not from ſome other Principle than the Glory of God, the Charity, and deſire of promoting the Salvation of Souls. Moreover, ſhould this addreſs be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106061:28"/>made to ſome of thoſe Doctors who follow different Opinions, upon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour they are obliged to examine all things, and retain what is beſt: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one will alledg in his own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, all the moſt plauſible Reaſons and Conſiderations which he can, and many times thoſe that are leaſt valid, are moſt ſpecious. After this can a Man of mean parts, find out in himſelf light enough, and diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to carry him through thoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, which make a ſeparation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men of far greater parts, and more refined Judgements than his Own.</p>
               <p>But laſt of all, what ſhall we ſay of the poor Labourer or ſimple Tradeſman, who has ever been bred in a Countrey, where ſome one of theſe Sects prevails? We know that ſuch a Sect forces thoſe of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, perfectly to acquieſce in it. That it requires every one to ſubmit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106061:29"/>any contradiction to all that it ſhall preſcribe: That there are ſome Sects, who ſuffer not their Followers to enter into any diſcuſſion of what they lay down to follow, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them to a blind obedience. As for Example, what can a poor Soul do, who has been born in the midſt of <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> where Reigns a moſt ſevere Inquiſition, or in the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt parts of <hi>Denmark,</hi> or <hi>Swedeland,</hi> where are none but Proteſtants, when he ſhall learn that there are other People elſewhere in great numbers, who are called Chriſtians, boaſting themſelves to have Truth in its greateſt Purity, and doom all to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Torments who are not of their Opinion? Is it not certain that a poor Wretch in this condition, not being able to have any commerce nor conference with thoſe of whom he hath been told this, will have ſo much more trouble in his Mind,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106061:29"/>by how much his paſſion is greater that ſtirs up in him a deſire of his own happineſs? Which makes us ſee the neceſſity of bringing together all Chriſtians under one common Principle: And this Principle muſt contain Maximes, eaſie, intelligible and indiſputable. In a word, this Principle muſt be ſuch, that it may produce Peace and Inward comfort, and guide all the Faithful, by the Practice of Holineſs, to the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Immortal Crown.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106061:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. The Second Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>That it deſtroys the ſtudy of Holineſs, and eſpecially the practice of Charity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Principal deſign of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and I dare ſay the only one, is to bring Men by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of its Miſteries, to the ſtudy of Virtue, and to conduct them by the practice of this Virtue, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Happineſs and Glory. So that we may ſay, that the ſacred Chain of our Salvation hath three Links, to wit, the knowledg of truths, the practice of virtues, and the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Happineſs. And if this Salvation be compared to a Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; The Revelations of the Goſpel,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106061:30"/>may be ſaid to be the Foundation and Baſis of it, Celeſtial Glory is the covering, and Virtue that which joyns theſe two extremes together, making us paſs from the knowledg, to the poſſeſſion of the Object known; where all our Felicity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. So that whatever gives any impediment to this knowledge, the ſame obſtructs the progreſs of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſtaggers the hope of Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city. The firſt receives no blow, whereof the two others feel not the Impreſſion. And this is ſeen in theſe Lamentable Diviſions, which not only caſt us into diſquiet, as hath been ſaid, but alſo in diſturbing Mens knowledg, they hinder Holineſs, and pervert the practice of Chriſtian Virtues. The principal part wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, conſiſts in the Piety and Zeal, which we bring to the ſervice of <hi>God.</hi> And the principal exerciſe of Piety conſiſts in the Sacred Commerce,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106061:31"/>which the Faithful entertain with their God, by Prayer. So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever troubles our Prayer, the ſame brings a notable prejudice to a life of Holineſs. If then, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> teaches us [1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.] the idle do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick contentions, which ariſe from the want of Unity between Husband and Wife, are capable to interrupt our Prayers, and blaſt the fruit of this ſaving exerciſe? What ſhall we ſay then of the Contentions which divide the Chriſtian Church, into ſo many different Societies? How can we expect that our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vows ſhould unite together to aſcend more readily to our common Father, whilſt our Opinions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently our Inclinations remain ſo contrary?</p>
               <p>One of the principal means re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired for our right obſerving of Holineſs, is the repoſe and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of the Soul: Sweetneſs alſo and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106061:31"/>moderation are neceſſary, which make us look upon things without any prejudice, and the engagement of particular Intereſts. If then (as we have plainly ſhewed) this Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion throws us into ſuch diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and trouble, every one may judg how prejudicial it is to the notions of true Piety. Is it not certain, that if we would employ in the ſtudy of Piety, and good Works, the time which we allow our ſelves, for the examining of all thoſe Queſtions, which divide us; We ſhould quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make great progreſs in the way which leads to Eternal Life? The Emperor <hi>Antoninus</hi> exhorted thoſe who were deſirous to advance in the practice of Moral Virtues, to deſiſt from the reading of Books, chiefly ſuch as treated of Philoſophy, as being only a hinderance to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. If, ſaid he, any ſhould perſwade thee to read, do thou immediately
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106061:32"/>anſwer, I have no time, to buſy my head about theſe things; I have a greater and more important affair in hand, which requires a Man's whole attendance. My buſineſs is to tame my paſſions, and to make my ſelf every day a more virtuous Man, and to diſcharge my principal duties. May we not in like manner ſay, to theſe curious Wits, who give up themſelves intirely to ſuch thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny queſtions? This is not that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye were called, Leave off all theſe contentions; You loſe the moſt precious thing in the World, which is your time. Rather ſtudy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a true Chriſtian, that is, to be humble, fearing God, loving your Neighbour, preſerving your Body in purity, avoiding evil, and continually endeavouring to edifie thoſe with whom you converſe.</p>
               <p>If Holineſs be no other thing than a precious Crown, compoſed of all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106061:32"/>Chriſtian and Moral Virtues, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there is none but will grant me that the faireſt flower of that Crown is Charity towards our Neighbour, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. Now this Virtue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in loving our Neighbour, as our ſelf; Conſidering that he bears the Characters of the Image of God; That we enter both one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Communion of the ſame Society, and that we are called to be made partakers together of one and the ſame Inheritance. This ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Virtue is ſo excellent, that ſome, with good reaſon, call it tho Soul of Religion, the Fountain of all other Virtues, or to ſpeak more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, Virtue it ſelf, which takes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Names, according to the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Subjects whereon it is exerciſed. It is called Piety, when it looks up towards Heaven, to pay Homage to its Soveraign, we call it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106061:33"/>Charity, when enclining towards the Earth, it ſtudies to do good to its Fellow-ſervants; In a word, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Names of other Virtues, as of Temperance, of Modeſty, of Humility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when it is reflected back upon its ſelf, by the Motions of that Legitimate Love, which it bears it ſelf. Therefore if this Monſter of Diviſion, be capable to deſtroy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which eſtabliſhes the Eſſence of Holineſs; It is manifeſt, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be conceived more preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to Virtue, than the diſ union and alienation of Mens minds. And as Charity propoſes nothing but Peace, Union, and Concord, For its aim is ſtraitly to tye the knots of a holy amity: There can nothing be ſo diametrically oppoſite to it, as Diviſion, which cutting all theſe knots, and breaking theſe ſacred Bonds, does divide all that which ſhould be moſt united.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106061:33"/>To confirm this truth; Let us make a parallel of the effects of this Charity, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> thus reckons up, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. with thoſe which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion produces. Charity is of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſpirit, diviſion is turbulent and unquiet: Charity is kind and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, Diviſion only ſpreads hatred and malice; Charity is not envious, but envy raigns particularly in divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, where each party reſpects the obligation of their proper Intereſts; Charity is not inſolent, nor puffed up with Glory, whereas Diviſion is fierce, proud, and inſupportable; It inſpires thoſe who poſſeſs it with a deſire to abaſe and oppreſs others, if it be poſſible, that they may raiſe up themſelves, and Rule without Competitor; Charity ſeeks not its own ends, is not diſpiteful, and thinks no evil. Theſe ill qualities are the true Characters of Diviſion, in which it hath no other end, than the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106061:34"/>of its own party, to the detriment of all others. Charity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyces not in injuſtice, but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the truth: Diviſion oppreſſes the truth, and is never pleaſed, but with unrighteouſneſs, and violence. Charity endures, believes, hopes and bears all things. Diviſion cauſes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions and jealouſies to ariſe, gives ill interpretations to actions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the moſt innocent words, and drives us into paſſion and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, into murmuring and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances. And to draw the laſt Line to this parallel, God grant that as Charity never fails, but is maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the very ruine of all that which is moſt Glorious, and moſt firm in Society: ſo on the other ſide, by the rule of contraries, that we may quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee this unhappy Diviſion utterly decay and ceaſe, by a perfect uniting of all Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106061:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The Third Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>That it makes Men Irreligious, and cauſes Atheiſme.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN all Diviſions, which tear in pieces Kingdomes and Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, each ſide at the firſt does boaſt by their Manifeſtoes and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they took not up Armes, but for the Publick Good, and for maintaining the Crown and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Prince; And although thoſe Parties be ſo contrary, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, that their Swords are drawn, and in a readineſs to decide their quarrel, yet both of them have the confidence to alledge in their Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the Juſtice of their cauſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106061:35"/>and intereſt of their Soveraign; whilſt in the end, all tend to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubverſion of the State, and total change of the Government. And it will many times happen, in theſe conteſts, that the moſt mutinous and moſt ſedicious, do make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of Soveraign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. So is it ordinarily ſeen, that in the diviſion of Opinions in Religion, every one proteſts, that no other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument or Intereſt perſwades him to follow the Religion that he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, but the real love of truth, and deſire of his Salvation: All thoſe who would be the promoters and ſpreaders of ſome new Opinion, ſhow an extraordinary Devotion and Zeal at the beginning; But by little and little all that degenerates, and all the overtures which Diviſion makes, ſerve but as ſo many doors, by which at laſt, Impiety Irreligion, and Atheiſme do ſlip in. 'Tis amidſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106061:35"/>theſe differences that we commonly ſee ſome new Religion thruſt in it ſelf among us, which differs but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little from the diſclaiming of all Religion. Juſt ſo was it by means of the divers Sects, which heretofore ſprang up in the Church, that the Doctrin of <hi>Mahomet</hi> has taken ſuch footing in the World; Every one knows how wide the Diviſion of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches was at that time. And I do not believe but that the great diverſity of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Religions, which we ſee at preſent in Chriſtianity, hath been the cauſe of this coldneſs and want of Devotion amongſt us, in what we call <hi>Christian Society.</hi> Inſomuch that Piety and Religion ſeem only to be left in full Authority amongſt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the Vulgar.</p>
               <p>This Evil ariſes from hence, that the greateſt part of Men either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or will not give themſelves the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106061:36"/>trouble of ſearching into theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Opinions, to determine which they might cloſe with; ſo they chooſe rather to believe nothing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, than to be always in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence about what they ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. As the great diverſity of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, which are preſcribed to a Patient, do very often make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe all, thinking it better to reſign up all to venture at once, rather than ſtand ſo long about making his choice of the Remedies which are propoſed to him. Some go towards it, but with ſuch a kind of negligence and natural ſloath, that makes them apprehend a great deal of trouble in it: And theſe eſteem it better to ſuſpend all manner of action, than undertake any thing, that requires ſo much care and intenſneſs of thought concerning it. Theſe are like lazy Souldiers, who ſuffer themſelves to be kill'd, rather than they'l couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106061:36"/>take up their Armes, and ſtand to their own defence: Or thoſe who, out of a deſperate Fury thruſt a Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger into their own Breaſts, for fear, leaſt their Enemy is preſſing upon them to do it.</p>
               <p>There are others who dare not venture upon this tryal, through the diſtruſt which they have of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and of their own power; They do not feel themſelves ſtrong enough to ſuſtain ſuch a weight, nor able to break through all thoſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties which they meet with. This obliges ſome, blindly to follow the firſt that is preſented them, and ſuffer themſelves to be led by thoſe, who pretend to have skill herein; Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing they are in a good condition, if they put themſelves under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of their Leaders: And others ſtand Newters, not daring to adhear to any Party, out of a Diſtruſt which they have, of all ſuch as offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106061:37"/>to them; And this it is, that cauſes Irreligion and Atheiſme. Yet are there ſome, whoſe Fault is not neglect of examining theſe different Queſtions, but the true Reaſon of it is, becauſe they are not indeed ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it. Such are all Peſants and Mechanicks, and others, who know nothing more, than what belongs to their employments, and who, being taken out of that, are as if they were in an unknown Country, where they are ignorant both of the wayes and Language: It puts them to a ſtand, as though they had neither ſenſe nor Motion; They make all their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and all the Service which they ſhould pay to God, to conſiſt in the well obſerving theſe outward actions of Religion, in which they have been trained up. Witneſs the poor Chriſtians of <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> all whoſe Religion is no more than juſt a ſhowing to thoſe who deſire to be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106061:37"/>informed of their belief, the Image of ſome Saint, which they carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with them: And others alſo, who think that if they know but how to make the ſign of the Croſs aright, may paſs for very good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Therefore, if, inſtead of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelling our ſelves about ſo many que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and controverſies, we would ſtudy to bring back the Chriſtian Doctrin, to its true Principles, which are but few in number, and eaſy for all ſorts of Perſons to comprehend, it would be the ready way to make true Chriſtians, who would know what is really eſſential in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and ſo would quickly be brought to a true piety, and to the fear of God, which is the only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>Here it may alſo be added, that this great diverſity of Opinions, begets a ſtrange prejudice in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Spirits: For there are many
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106061:38"/>who would make us believe, that truth is ſo evident and perceivable, by all where it is reveal'd, that it ſhines as the Sun, which dims the light of all the other Stars. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they conclude, that if Chriſtian Religion contains thoſe ſaving truths that came from God, were brought down from Heaven to Earth, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Glory and Miracles, it would immediately obſcure with its ſplendour all ſeeming truths, which ſtrive to have a counterfeit Luſter to reſemble it. When therefore they ſee that every one of theſe different Opinions upholds it ſelf by ſuch probable Reaſons, that many are ſtaggered at the conſideration of them: They cannot be perſwaded that this Gold is to be found in the Earth, becauſe it does not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately diſcover them its gliſtering light. And as they cannot conceive that it is fit for them to remain one
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106061:38"/>moment in ſuſpence of ſeparating truth from falſhood and errour, they forſake both one and the other, to ſecure themſelves from the danger of being forced to a new change, thoſe Perſons would certainly refuſe to take a Sum of Money, if offered them, out of a diſtruſt, that they ſhould not know the Coines, and that they ſhould not diſcern falſe Money from good; whence we may judge, how great the prejudice is, which this Diviſion brings to Mens Salvation. An unhappy deſign, that under the pretence of an exact ſearch for the truth, deſtroys the principal effect of Chriſtian Religion, which is the Salvation and comfort of Souls!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106061:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. The Fourth Effect of Diviſion. <hi>That it keeps back all thoſe who are without, and breeds in them a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of Christian Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe preaching of the Goſpel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were a publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to invite Men to liſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Enſigns of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> It is undeniable, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever obſtructs this Holy Summons is contrary to the intent and purpoſe of the Goſpel, and troubles the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Eternal Raign of the Son of God; And this ſame is one of the principal effects of the Diviſion of Chriſtians. Thoſe who are without the bounds of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106061:39"/>as <hi>Turks, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> may juſtly reproach us, with the want of a true underſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves. Reſolve how to ſettle (will they ſay) your different Opinions, before you go about to perſwade us to follow you. Firſt unite your ſelves together, and then we will conſider whether or no we ſhall unite with you. And ſince u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and verity are inſeparable; How, in this great difference of your Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſhall we be aſſured that you will propound the truth to us? And certainly there can be no great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſcandal to our Religion, in the ſight of thoſe without, than this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Diviſion. The <hi>Sieur dela Boulaye</hi> [Chap. 18.] In his Voyages to the <hi>Levant,</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Turks</hi> perceiving this vitious exceſs of ſtrife, and multitude of Diviſions amongſt Chriſtians, have confirmed themſelves, by this means in their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106061:40"/>own way, and think God to be the Author of them. 'Tis by reaſon of this, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, [Rom. 2.] That the Name of God is deſpiſed, becauſe of us, among the Gentiles. And yet the bad lives, and extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances of particular Perſons, do not bring ſo much Prejudice to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, as the Dividents of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions in its Doctrine. Of the firſt it may be ſaid, that theſe are but the faults of certain Perſons, whoſe profeſſion is not anſwerable to their Religion; That that may be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, though they are criminal, who pretend to follow it. But when the evil is in the Opinions; It may be thought that the defect is in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it ſelf. So that they have ſome Reaſons to offer their Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and to ſuſpect the Truth of the whole. Therefore if it be the purity of the Doctrine, rather than the deportment of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106061:40"/>that muſt draw us to one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; without all queſtion, that which reſults from this Doctrine, will make a greater impreſſion upon Mens ſpirits, than that which only regards the manners of ſome few Men.</p>
               <p>'Tis generally obſerved that things are not maintained, but by the aide of that which firſt contributed to their production. The ſame influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Heavens, which made thoſe Seeds ſprout up, that the Earth has been intruſted with, ſerve like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to raiſe the Plants to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Therefore ſome ambitious and unſteady brains have taken occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by the Diviſion of Chriſtians, to give birth to a Sect, which hath utterly departed from the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Principles of Chriſtianity; For it was by the means of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union, that a new Religion hath been formed, and a falſe Prophet ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106061:41"/>in the room of the: Eternal Son of God, who alone inſpired all the true Prophets. It is not to be wondred, ſuch Diviſions continuing in the Church, if theſe poor miſled Souls remain confirmed in their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And ſince that which firſt alienated them from us, ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains; the averſion which they have to our miſteries, remains likewiſe. So long as the <hi>Roman</hi> Armies were well united, that their Commanders held a perfect underſtanding amongſt themſelves, and their Souldiers were kept in a true obedience and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to their Orders: Other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons endeavoured to procure their amity with great eagerneſs; They eſteemed it a great Glory to enter into alliance with this People, and many have made no difficulty, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Yoke, to whoſe Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they thought all others ought to ſubmit: But ſo ſoon as miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106061:41"/>happen'd between their Generals and Souldiers, and revolts in the Subjects. Other States deſpiſed their Alliance, and took up Armes againſt them, plainly ſeeing that they were not invincible, ſince they were ſubject to Diviſion. Juſt ſo, our diſunion makes us an object of the contempt and averſion of all other people. After this, can we think it ſtrange that ſo many Exhortations, Sermons, and Writings, which have paſs'd continually amongſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſhould make ſo few Proſelites? In the Apoſtles time, one Sermon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone converted many Thouſands of Infidels to the Faith. At the end of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon Three Thouſand Souls, by Baptiſm ranged themſelvs under the Standard of the Croſs. [Act. 2] It was alſo at this time that all Chriſtians dwelt together with one common accord, and had all but one heart, and one Soul. At
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106061:42"/>this preſent we drive back by our Diviſions, thoſe whom we invite by our Exhortations. But if it ſhould be objected, that the Church makes now great progreſs in the <hi>Indies;</hi> I dare ſay, with pardon for my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that theſe poor people have not yet attained to the knowledg of our diviſions, and that if they ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, their Zeal would quickly wax cold, and all theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts would be of no long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</p>
               <p>When the Proteſtants firſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo long as they kept an Uniformity in their Opinions, they made marvellous progreſs, the Union which was amongſt them drew a great part of Europe to their profeſſion: But ſo ſoon as they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided themſelves into ſeveral bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, they have put a ſtop to their conqueſts, and had no further
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106061:42"/>thought, than to maintain themſelvs both thoſe whom they have forſaken, and ſuch as have forſaken them.</p>
               <p>And it is not only from the ill example of this diviſion, that ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Faith are driven from it: They are led thereunto by the very intrigues and ſtratagems of the Chriſtians, who are ſo ſeparated and divided among themſelves. Their Diviſion creates ſuch animoſity one againſt the other, that they do their utmoſt endeavour, to hinder thoſe who have an earneſt deſire to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſtianity, from entring into any other Chriſtian communion but their own. There are others who go further, for they hold it as a true Maxime. That it is better for a <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Mahometan,</hi> to perſiſt in his old Errour, than to thruſt himſelf into ſome of the Chriſtian Societies, which they diſapprove. So that as it is impoſſible for Iron equally
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106061:43"/>drawn between two Loadſtones, to move either towards the one, or the other. So theſe different ſolicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which Chriſtians make to draw Infidels to them, leaves them in a neutral ſtate, not knowing which ſide they ſhould take, nor to which they ſhould determine their Judgments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106061:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. The Fifth Effect of this Diviſion. <hi>Trouble in Church and State.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Evil of this Diviſion is not limited only to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but all Societies, as well Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, as Civil, have too great a feeling of it: For we dayly ſee ſtrange Tempeſts happen in both, which had no other cauſe for the forming of them, than this ſad diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union. And has not the Church much reaſon to complain, that thoſe who are called her Children ſhould tear out her Bowels? That ſhe can expect nothing but death even from thoſe to whom ſhe hath given life? Since they to whom ſhe continually
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106061:44"/>adminiſters the ſacred Milk of her pure Doctrine, and of her wholſome Inſtructions, do give her ſo many grievous wounds, as they form Sects in her; In multiplying they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Her, and each ſtriving to draw her to their ſide, at laſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſeen to remain, but her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and broken pieces. And what is more; theſe deplorable Reliques of the Church, have likewiſe been ſo miſerably handled, that ſhe is no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be known; inſomuch that they might rather be taken for the parts of ſome miſhapen Monſter, than for the Members of the Divine Spouſe of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> waſhed in the Blood of her dear Lord, and clothed with the Sacred Robe of his Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>But that I may not be thought to aggravate theſe things, and raiſe them with an Hyperbole: Let us but conſider the preſent face of the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106061:44"/>Church; Is it not true that we ſhall have much ado to meet any one of theſe Societies, (which call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Church, and attribute the truth ſolely to themſelves,) where theſe ill Characters are not to be ſeen? Firſt, a certain high conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Opinion of the Principles they have embraced, which creates in them a blind perſwaſion without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining it, and whereof not any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid reaſon can be given. Birth, Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Worldly Intereſts, and other engagements of this nature, together with a kind of negligence, and a fear of being accounted inconſtant, and unſetled, if they ſhould turn to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party; Theſe things, I ſay, have ordinarily a greater influence for the eſtabliſhment of them in their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, than Reaſon and Conſcience have: All which is followed by a certain obſtinacy, not to call it ſelf-conceitedneſs, in maintaining their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106061:45"/>belief, at any rate whatſoever. There are thoſe who many times do ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, on this occaſion, all that they hold deareſt in the World, even to their very lives; which paſſes in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very One of theſe Societies, for an exquiſit Zeal, and an examplary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. Nor is there any one of theſe Sects, which has not a Catalogue of its Confeſſors, and that cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce its Roll of Martyrs. But how many are there of theſe Martyrs, who if they had been demanded to give a reaſon of the Doctrine, for which they made ſo much conſtancy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, would have been gravelled, and have little to anſwer to the leaſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that might have been propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them? Many times falſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are maintained with as much heat, as the True. Alſo Illuſions and Impoſtures do make as ſtrong Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon our Spirits, as real Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts. Now this obſtinacy draws af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106061:45"/>it an extreme averſion to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religions, and even to all other Chriſtian Societies: It either accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them of blindneſs, or of ſtupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or of malice. 'Tis nothing elſe, ſay they, but fleſhly intereſt, that ſeems a Foundation of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; They reproach them, that their Opinions are altogether deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to true Piety; that they hurry Men into Superſtition and to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or elſe to Libertiniſme or Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme. And ſome there are, who are pointed out by others, as if they were frightful Monſters. In a word, any proteſtation, or any declaration, which they make, that it is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine they loath, and not the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who take it up; That it is the Error they deteſt, but that they have charity and compaſſion, for ſuch as are miſled, is enough with them: Which yet ſhall never make me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, But that the precedent quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106061:46"/>are accompanied with a great Animoſity of Spirit, againſt thoſe who are not of the ſame Opinion. For how can we ſincerely love thoſe, whom we look upon as Enemies to God, and Diſciples of Satan, whoſe Lot and Portion is Hell, where they ſhall be made a Prey to the Devils? Are there not likewiſe very dreadful Examples, in what manner they have reciprocally treated one another, in thoſe places where they are mingled together. The weak employ ſuch armes as are moſt convenient againſt their Adverſaries, which are inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and reproaches; the powerful ſtraight paſs to action; there is no craft nor ſubtilty, no violence nor cruelty, which theſe People ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t not a work, utterly to exterminate ſuch as follow a different profeſſion from theirs. The <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes the Proteſtant, in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where he is ſtrongeſt. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106061:46"/>he requites him where he has the Power and Authority in his own hands. And amongſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, thoſe who are of different O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, are not treated more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. Heretofore the Chriſtians complained much, that the <hi>Pagans</hi> would force them to ſacrifice to their Gods, and quit their Religion. [<hi>Tertul. Apolog.</hi> 28.] They grounded not their complaint on any other Reaſon than this, that Religion, as they affirmed, ought to be an act of a pure and free Mind. But now a days Chriſtians do the ſame thing towards Chriſtians. We have ſeen times, where tortures and the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt puniſhments, have been uſed by Chriſtians, for afflicting other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and for no other cauſe but their not being of the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and perſwaſions. And now after this, who can take it ill that I have no more repreſented the <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:106061:47"/>as the Ship which the Son of God conveyeth ſafe amidſt the ſtormes, wherewith ſhe is continually batter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; But to the lamentable wracks of a Veſſel, daſht in pieces, not by the rage and fury of contrary Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but by the negligence of thoſe within her, and miſunderſtanding of her Conductors.</p>
               <p>This Evil is alſo very communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative; 'Tis like a Gangrene, which never ſtays in one place, but corrupts all the neighbouring parts; States, and all Bodies Politique are very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the effects of this Diviſion. We might ſay of this evil, as of the Leproſie deſcribed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that it not only infects Men, but the very Towns and Places where they dwell. I dare affirm, that of Thirty Wars, which have happened in Europe, within theſe Hundred and fifty years, five and twenty have had the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of Religion for the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106061:47"/>of them, or at leaſt, that they have either been accompanied or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by ſome Intereſts of Religion. If any would throw the Apple of Diſcord into a Nation, to trouble it, and raiſe civil Wars at home, to the end, that Foreiners might have an opportunity of attacking it; They need but uſe means to cauſe ſome differences to be moved about the Government of the Church; Find ſome fault with the Ornaments of the Altars; Cloath in a different manner thoſe who are to adminiſter Divine Service; or introduce ſome diverſity in the Liturgy, and in the Publique Prayers. This will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to diſturb the Peace of a Nation, and abſolutely turn it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide down. Examples of this are ſo freſh, and ſo dreadful amongſt us, that I need not produce them to confirm what I lay before you. If we would favour the Rebellion of any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106061:48"/>Country, or back the pretenſions of ſome Uſurper; 'Tis but publiſhing that the reaſon why we take up arms in their favour, is to give Liberty to weak and tender Conſciences, and to be inſtrumental, in giving poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Chriſtians a freedom of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God Almighty, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all the Exerciſes of Devotion without conſtraint. There is nothing impoſſible to be effected under this ſpecious pretence: There is no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of exceſs and violence, which on theſe occaſions they do not dreſs up in the Cloke of Piety and Zeal. <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, there are no ſewds to be compared to thoſe which ſpring from diſſenting in Religion: And till theſe ceaſe, and an union be made, we muſt never expect to ſee that the States of Chriſtendom, ſhould agree together, to reſiſt the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106061:48"/>of their Profeſſion. &amp; put a ſtop to their progreſs; Who prevail by means of our Diviſions, and advance their Conqueſts by help of our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtandings. If one only place ſcituate in an Iſland, which was all Enemies to it, were capable to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, for ſo long a Time, the whole <hi>Ottoman</hi> Power: What would it do, if the Armies of all Chriſtians were joyned together to Repreſs the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of an enemy, deteſting ſo much the Name of a Chriſtian? I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that he is not victorious, but becauſe we do not defend our ſelves. He gains no ground, but meerly for want of our Oppoſition; and gives us no wounds, but by thoſe gaſhes which wo give our ſelves. If we would ſtir by Agreement, for the glory of our common Maſter, all thoſe advantages which we promiſe our ſelves, from the Victories we gain over our Fellow-brethren, are
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106061:49"/>not comparable to thoſe which would accrue to us by our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of ſtrangers. And let not thoſe Chriſtian Princes, whoſe Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories lye far diſtant from <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> flatter themſelves in their own thoughts, with the advantage of their ſcituation; For thoſe Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, which ſerve at preſent for a Bulwark to Chriſtendom, being once maſtered by the <hi>Turks,</hi> they will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily force a paſſage into the heart of the moſt remote Countrys. If they but once have a liberty of entering upon our Borders and Confines, they will ſoon ſtrike up an Alarm with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the very Bowels of Europe; And it is too well known, how ſome of theſe parts have lately been weakned. I wiſh with all my heart, that the Drums and Trumpets of theſe Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, may be a means to gather Us once more together, and be as a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to put us in mind of uniting our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106061:49"/>ſelves quickly, and labouring altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our own preſervation.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, this conſideration might be added to the precedent ones, to make us ſee the Evil, that this Diviſion cauſes in States. Let us ſuppoſe that in a Kingdom, or any other Chriſtian State, thoſe who Govern it, ſhould perceive that they have been miſtaken in the Opinion; which they have held; and that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have not the truth on their ſide, they are in danger of loſing their Souls. I dare affirm, that the Nature of this Diviſion is ſuch, that it would be almoſt impoſſible to procure their own Salvation, and the Salvation of thoſe who are under their Authority. The Intereſts of State are ſo mixed, and woven with thoſe of Religion; The intrigues and alliances, which are made with thoſe of the ſame communion, are ſo ſtrong, that in going about to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106061:50"/>them, it would endanger a loſs of all. As for Example, who does not conceive, that if a King, who is a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick ſhould come to believe that the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Religion are not ſound, that (as the Proteſtants alledg) they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain certain Principles that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the Salvation of Souls; this Prince would not meet with impregnable difficulties to ſet his Conſcience at reſt? Is it not certain that ſo ſoon as he ſhould diſcover his Thoughts, his Subjects would riſe up in Rebellion againſt Him? The whole Body of his State would oppoſe his Deſigns, and his Allies would forſake him, to ſide with that Party, that ſhould be againſt Him? The ſame might be ſaid of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Princes. The Politicians, who oppoſe themſelves to any change or innovation in Religion, of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo ever it be, who look upon it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106061:50"/>as a Flame that muſt be quenched in the inſtant, would render all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of a Prince unprofitable, that ſhould have any ſuch thoughts. Therefore by this it is evident, that it is the Ground and Intereſt of all Chriſtian States, to endeavour the healing of theſe Diviſions; as well for their own ſubſiſtence and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as for the ſafety and quiet of the Conſciences of thoſe who Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:51"/>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:106061:51"/>
            <head>THE <hi>RE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITING</hi> OF CHRISTIANITY</head>
            <head>PART II. <hi>Of the Cauſes of this Diviſion which is among Chriſtians.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>That the Frame and Temper of Men's Minds doth much contribute to this Evil.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHatſoever things paſs through the Hands of Men, they alwayes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that quality which is predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106061:52"/>in them; As Waters take their Tincture, from the Channels through which they run; if the Channels be impure, the Waters quickly loſe that Purity, which from the Fountain Head they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd. So Chriſtian Doctrine, the ſame which was given us by the Son of God, and propoſed to us by his Apoſtles, is moſt pure and moſt Holy: But it has been much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ill qualities of ſuch as have handled it, ſince thoſe bleſſed Times; It hath paſſed through ſoul hands, which have made it loſe much of its Original Beauty. The Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal paſſion, and that which chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raigns amongſt Men, is Vanity and Pride; and that likewiſe is it, which has given the firſt ſoil to Chriſtian Doctrine. There have been ſome, who have thought it too plain and too courſe, for Wits higher than the common Level. Every one of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106061:52"/>thoſe who have fancied themſelves to have any degree of Light above others, have had a mind to cloath it after their own mind. Many have believed that they had a right to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe their Judgments in the moſt profound Myſteries; Yea, ſome have been ſo raſh and bold, as to add of their own Heads, what they eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neceſſary to its perfection: and this it is that has given a beginning to the great diverſity of Opinions, which are at this Day in Religion.</p>
               <p>Hence has it come to paſs, that ſome learned Doctors having made the firſt advance of their particular Opinions in Religion, others coming afterwards (thinking no leſs of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves than the former) have taken a liberty of examining their Tenents, and have further thought they were obliged to overthrow them, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh others, by which means they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106061:53"/>hoped to make themſelves famous, in being the Authors of a new Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and Founders of a Sect. The firſt carried by the ſame Motive, which at the beginning had induced them to propoſe new Doctrines, were not willing to recant them; For it is not ſo much the perſwaſion of the Truth, of what they have broached, that obliges Men to perſiſt in it, as the fear and ſhame of diſowning that which they have once aſſerted, and that new-comers ſhould be able to diſcover their faults, and teach them any thing. So that every one ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up for their own Notions, and being unwilling to let themſelves be run down, and vanquiſhed; This impertinent ſelf-conceitedneſs, has laid the Foundation of theſe great Diviſions.</p>
               <p>This Evil might in ſome meaſure have been ſuffer'd, if ſuch had been contented to declare their Opinions,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106061:53"/>as the meer productions of humane Wit, and if particular Perſons keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them within their own breaſts, had left others the liberty of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, either to receive, or reject them, according to the judgement that they ſhould make of them. But as when ſome thinking they want credit to eſtabliſh what they are deſirous to put in practiſe, have commonly recourſe to a ſuperiour Authority, whereby they procure that to paſs in their favour, which otherwiſe would not have been conſidered of: So every party contending in matters of Religion, and not believing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſufficiently ſtrengthned by their own Reaſons, and Authority, does preſently declare it to be the Intereſt of God, and his cauſe that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, and every one of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, proteſts that whoſoever rejects what he delivers, rejects the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Doctrine, throws down the Pillars
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106061:54"/>of Chriſtian Religion, walks out of the true Church, and expoſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Eternal Damnation. So that drawing thus ſtraightly the Bonds which ſhould engage Men's Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, in their Parties they have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned particular animoſities, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened the Diviſion, and rendred the Evil more incurable. For whither will not the Wit of Man carry him, when he ſhall be poſſeſſed with an Opinion, that whatſoever he does, tends to the Glory of God, and the Salvation of his own Soul?</p>
               <p>There are two different ſorts of Spirits, to whom the Doctrin of the Goſpel is propos'd, the firſt are bold and active; the ſecond timorous and always very diſtruſtful of themſelves: The former eaſily undertaking to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh new Opinions, and to give begining to Diviſion; the latter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes not a little to the fomenting &amp; encreaſing of it, through their timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106061:54"/>and facility, not daring to depart from what their Predeceſſors have preſcribed them. And as in Seditions the froward and buſy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits are they which raiſe the tumults, and ſtir up others; and the Rabble being prepared by ſome artificial and plauſible Declaration, finiſh the diſorder, by the liberty which they give themſelvs, and is allowed them by the grand Mutineers: So it is in Religion; for the ordinary People be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing naturally ignorant, cannot hit upon the right way, but by chance; It muſt be their great good fortune, or to ſay better, a Divine conduct which muſt guide them to it, and not any choice or ſearch of their own. And yet it is the moſt inferiour ſort of People, that are the fierceſt and moſt eager in maintaining the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which they blindly follow, and whereof they for the moſt part have but little knowledge and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106061:55"/>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> complains, in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, that the <hi>Pagans</hi> condemned the Doctrin of the Chriſtians, which they were ignorant of: and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians are there now a days, who condemn the Opinions of other Chriſtians, without knowing them? 'Tis therefore from this popular and blind paſſion, that the Grand Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Politick Heads of Factions ſerve themſelves to ſtrengthen their Sides, advance their deſigns, and take away all means of Reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween party and party.</p>
               <p>Now theſe Heads of Sects, and all thoſe, who following their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, pretend to have a ſhare in their Glory, do play another Game, to attain more eaſily to their Ends; which is this: they ſtrive many times to engage the Politicians in their Cauſe, making them believe that their Doctrine is the moſt proper to hold the common people in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106061:55"/>and in obedience to their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours; that it prevents all kinds of Inſurrections, Seditions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions. In effect, I believe there is ſcarce any Sect of Chriſtians, which does not boaſt to have this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage above others; they tax all thoſe who oppoſe their Tenets with build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon ſuch Foundations, as are only fit to bring diſturbance upon States, and to alienate the affections of Subjects from their Princes; at leaſt they affirm that others have Principles which do not preſs home enough this Article, of the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which is due to Magiſtrates. 'Tis well known what the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks ſay of the Doctrine of the Proteſtants on this Subject; 'Tis alſo well enough known on the other ſide, how the Proteſtants reproach them, by Reaſon of the power which they ſeem to give to a Forein Nation to Conquer ſuch as deny Obedience
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106061:56"/>to the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Authority. Whence it comes to paſs, that according to the Face which the Politicians ſet on theſe things, they favour thoſe, whom they ſuppoſe do contribute moſt by their Doctrine; to the peace and quiet of States, which is their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign good. Likewiſe when a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is once eſtabliſhed in any State, it is the prudence and care of thoſe who govern, that makes them hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a change, by reaſon of the great diſorders which may ariſe from it. Therefore thoſe Doctors who have no other aim, than that of maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Opinions which they have eſtabliſhed or embraced, do moſt of all their endeavour to bring into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, with the Magiſtrates of their Country, all of different Tenets from theirs. They make them believe that all thoſe who are not of the ſame mind with them, go about to undermine the Foundations of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106061:56"/>that they might ſubſtitute ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in its roome; Thus by their ſubtilty they Arm the Secular Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, againſt thoſe who would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Doctrines perchance were innocent, or better Founded than theirs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106061:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>That there has never yet been made a true diſtinction in Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, of what is really Eſsential and Fundamental, and what is not.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough the minds of thoſe who have embraced Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, may be diverſly diſpoſed; yet they all agree in this one Point; that there are certain Doctrines in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which are Eſſential, and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental, and others likewiſe of leſs importance. They all acknowledge that there are ſome, from which they cannot depart, without doing a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt prejudice to Religion, and to the Salvation of Souls; and that there are alſo others, to which they may adhere without wounding their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106061:57"/>But there could never yet any Boundaries be agreed upon, which ſhould be eſtabliſhed for the right ſetling all People in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and natural Limits: Every one would make his own Opinion paſs for Fundamental, and abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation. Whereas had we but well diſtinguiſhed betwixt theſe two ſorts of Doctrines, had we but laid good Foundations to keep theſe Tenets hereafter from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confuſed, this Evil of which we complain, might eaſily be remedied, and all Parties might be Re-united, as I undertake to make appear to You, in the Third Part of this Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, who does not evidently ſee, that for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly how to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two ſorts of Doctrines; the greateſt part of the Diviſions which are amongſt Chriſtians, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106061:58"/>to ariſe? How many queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are there, as unprofitable as cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, which have made a ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Men's Judgments? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſons, without ever having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ammed or underſtood them, have ſided ſome with one, and ſome with the other, only that they might not be ſuſpected to be without Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without Devotion, and without Knowledg? How many Diſputes likewiſe are there, which have no other Foundation, than certain dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent terms and expreſſions, whilſt all agree in the ſubſtances, and make all their quarrels but about words? 'Tis certain, that would they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Foundation of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, without paſſion, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, they would be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for having loſt ſo much time, and expreſt ſo much heat about a thing which merited it not. Every one knows how many diſputes the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106061:58"/>ſubject of Grace hath cauſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks. 'Tis well known with what ardour the Defenders of an Irreſpective Science, which they attribute to God, have maintained their Doctrine againſt thoſe who eſtabliſh an Abſolute De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. This is that which has formed two Parties amongſt their Doctors; This Difference has continued, and is renewed in our time betwixt the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> although under other terms. There is no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ignorant, unto what a degree of Diviſion they have come about this buſineſs, and the ſtrange conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are apprehended from it. In the mean time, how a new Doctor who hath cauſed the Memoires of Grace to be printed, maintains that all the difference, is but only in words. He undertakes to put an end to it, by ſhowing that they all agree in the Foundations, and are all
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106061:59"/>in the ſame mind with St. <hi>Auguſtin, Fulgentius,</hi> St. <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> all the School men, and the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> If it be ſo, who will not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, that the like thing may not poſſibly have happened, in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points, wherein (to our misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune) different Opinions have made a ſeparation and diviſion?</p>
               <p>I place in the rank of Queſtions, which are not eſſential and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in Religion, ſuch as are made about the buſineſs of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, and the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies inſtituted for ruling the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour part of its Worſhip. For how much ſtir has been made concerning thoſe things, which have no other ground, than the general Rule pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> namely, <hi>That all things be done with Order and Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Church!</hi> 'Tis ſufficient ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore, that <hi>in theſe Matters,</hi> we have always before our eyes, that which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106061:59"/>may advance the Glory of God, and edifie his Church. For indeed we may dreſs in a different manner, the proper means for obtaining ſo good an end. The uſe and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this general Rule, might be left to the Liberty of each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, to do what they ſhould judg moſt expedient, according to the Circumſtances of the Place, times, diſpoſitions of Mens Spirits, and ſuch like. They ſhould only take heed of introducing in theſe things ſome practice, which might be directly oppoſite to any of the eſſential and fundamental Doctrines. Some require that the Teachers of the Church ſhould be equal, and others would have a Superiority and Inferiority amongſt them. Some are for an outward Pomp in the Church, and others would have a great plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Some believe that the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Places of Devotion,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106061:60"/>breed a reſpect to the exerciſe, and others think that the meanneſs of the place, takes off the thoughts of the faithful from material carnal things, to lift them upward to thoſe which are Coeleſtial and Divine. Some love Muſick, and the ſound of melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Inſtruments in Divine Service: and others ſay, that it diſturbs the mind, and carries away the devotion, which ſhould be fixt in thoſe Holy places. Some are of Opinion that the Riches of the Miniſtry, their Train, and outward Pomp, gains them the veneration of the People, who are apt otherwiſe to deſpiſe them: Others judg that the pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſimplicity of the Miniſters of the Church, does better accord with the Genius of the Goſpel, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce more ſaving effects in the minds of Men, than all Worldly ſplendour. It is in theſe kinds of Queſtions and Differences, that I
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106061:60"/>ſhall let you ſee we ſhould bear one with another; for I hold, that there may happen occaſions, where one of theſe practices may be moſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and moſt edifying, and others, or that which is oppoſite to it, may likewiſe prove of very great benefit; always provided, that order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency be preſerved; Thus muſt there be a mutual Toleration amongſt Chriſtians, and a charitable and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly ſupport one towards another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:106061:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>That Men have departed from the true Fundamentals of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to take up others which have nothing of Solidity in them, and which put theſe Diviſions amongst Them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'TIs a general Opinion amongſt all Chriſtians, that it is from God alone that we muſt receive the Articles of our Faith, and the Rule of our Actions. They agree alſo in this, that it is in his Word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that thoſe two things are compriz'd, and that it is from thence, as from two Fountains, that they muſt be drawn down to us. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils themſelves, namely thoſe which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106061:61"/>are called General, and to which ſome Chriſtians do attribute as much authority and infallibility, as to the Holy Scriptures, confirm this truth. For they have never undertaken to decide any point of Religion, but by the Holy Scriptures, They have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that they ought to aſcend up thither for eſtabliſhing of any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which muſt have power and authority amongſt Chriſtians. And yet have we departed inſenſibly from this principle. We have quitted this ſaving Tenet, by attributing to Man, that which is not due, but to God alone. We have made ſuch Doctrines as are meerly humane, to paſs crowded amongſt thoſe which are handed down to us from God. Juſt as they put off falſe Money by making it gliſter as much as may be, and then mixing it amongſt ſuch as is currant Coin, that it may not be ſuſpected. This is it that has given
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106061:62"/>ſcope to contentions, and afterwards been the grand cauſe of Diviſion. Some have been of Opinion that whatſoever ſpecious pretences, and whatſoever plauſible names have been given to the deciſions of the moſt famous Aſſemblies, are all this while but Humane Sentiments, which ought to be examined before they are received. They ſay that they are but particular Men, who have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed their Opinions in theſe Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; That many times in theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, 'tis the credit, readineſs of wit, eloquence, or ſome force of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument more ſpecious than ſolid, which makes theſe Opinions paſs for Articles of Faith. That thoſe particular Perſons who compoſe theſe Aſſemblies may be miſtaken, notwithſtanding all their Lights and Knowledge; That by conſequence, a Company of them, how numerous ſoever they be, are ſubject to defects,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106061:62"/>and to the errours of the Members whereof they are compoſed. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That the very diverſity which is ſometimes ſound in the deciſions made by them, juſtifies enough their Opinion, and makes us ſee that all theſe deciſions are ſubject to tryal. Others who are of a different ſence, maintain that without the deciſions of the Councils, we ſhould have but an imperfect Rule of our Belief. That the Holy Scripture does not comprehend all that which is taught us in the Church. That there are alſo many things in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that have need of explaining and interpretation. That on theſe occaſions, there is none to whom we can have better recourſe, than to the Church, to whom God has promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ordinary conduct of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. That the Church cannot make her Voice be better underſtood, and declare to us her ſence, in a faſhion
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106061:63"/>more authentique, than when ſhe is repreſented, and as it were united in theſe Solemn Aſſemblies. They are perſwaded, that when ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly is lawfully gathered, it does of Right enjoy an Infallibility, equal to that of the Holy Scripture, that it is God himſelf, who ſpeaks as much in one, as the other.</p>
               <p>In the mean time both one and the other, agree in this point, that the Scripture is infallible, that it is the foundation of the truth, and the ſoveraign Rule of all Holineſs. The latter alſo pretend, that although they plead in favour of the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and infallibility of the Church, they find argument enough in the Scriptures, for maintaining their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and confounding of Errour. But let us, for the preſent, lay by this controverſy of the Authority of the Church, and return back to that principle, which all agree upon. It
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106061:63"/>may be we may draw Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections enough from thence, ſo that we ſhall not be obliged to enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this other Diſpute; which ſhall be more particularly examined in the third Part of this Treatiſe. Let us therefore only hear what <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſays upon this Subject. <hi>Apolog. Chap.</hi> 47. Where giving a Reaſon of the Diviſions which he ſaw in his time about Chriſtian Religion; He ſays that, <hi>Thoſe who have ſeparated themſelves from the Communion of the Church, have in the doing it, violated their faith to Jeſus Chriſt; For he it is that hath taught us the rule of truth, which he cauſed to be delivered to us by thoſe holy Men, who had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to hear his Word, and receive his divine Inſtructions; That all which is not conformable to that Rule, has been invented by new Doctors, who came not till after thoſe Bleſsed Diſciples of the Son of God.</hi> In this manner hath this
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106061:64"/>worthy Man aſcended up to the very Fountain Head of this Evil, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the Original of thoſe miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Diviſions. And St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in that remarkable paſſage againſt <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imin</hi> the <hi>Arrian, Let us lay aſide</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>all prejudices which we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, I from the Council of</hi> Nice, <hi>and thou from that of</hi> Arimini; <hi>Let us both one and the other be guided by the Authority of the Holy Scripture, which is no partial witneſs, but is as well common to one, as to the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, as when a Man hath once given way to ſome dangerous Principle, what care ſoever he takes to avoid the ill conſequences therof, he is ſure to fall inſenſibly upon them. Likewiſe whatſoever corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive may be brought for the taking away from the Antimony its malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant qualities, there ſhall neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs break forth ſome ill effects of it: So this Doctrine being once ſetled,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106061:64"/>that Men muſt be conſulted and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, concerning the Articles of Faith, we do give them by little and little an Authority, which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains only to him, who is truth it ſelf. The conſequence of which is, that we become in a condition of acquieſcing blindly on whatſoever the Caprichio's of Men can invent in matters of Religion. Every one believes himſelf to have as much right herein, as his Companion; Every one endeavours to make his particular Opinions paſs for eſſential truths; Every one condemns as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, and as People out of the way of Salvation, all thoſe who do not ſubmit themſelves abſolutely to their Rule: In brief, every one main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, that there is no true Church, but that which receives the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he has promoted, to whom alone belongs the Right of Governing all that which concerns
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106061:65"/>Religion. And although many make a difficulty of attributing inſallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Church; nevertheleſs they hold that they ought to ſubmit to theſe deciſions, at leaſt, if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cannot paſs for Deciders. All which has much contributed to the forming of Diviſion, and to the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting it, after it is kindled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:106061:65"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>That the diſlike which has been had at the ſimplicity of Chriſtian Religion, has been an occaſion, that Men have given it a different aſpect from that which it had in its beginning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Do not believe that there is any Chriſtian, who will not agree with me, that Chriſtianity was never more pure, more Holy, and more proper to induce its Profeſſors to Vertue, than in its Birth. That was a time wherein the ſaving Principles of the Goſpel, were only received from the mouth of the Son of God, and from thoſe holy Men whom he had inſpired. This was the true Golden Age of the Church, abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Saints, in Confeſſors, and in
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106061:66"/>Martyrs. And I believe that this truth will alſo be granted me, that then at that time when Chriſtian Religion was ſo pure, and exempt from Errour, its Doctrine was alſo moſt ſimple and moſt naked; It was free from all thoſe ſubtil queſtions, which ſome cauſed to be ſtatted up in the ſucceding Ages. It was not ſubjected to the burthenſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of ſo many Ceremonies, which are as ſtrange habits and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, wherewith it has been ſince cloathed. There are to be found amongſt us two ſorts of Perſons, which have much contributed to this Evil. The firſt are thoſe ſubtil Spirits, who beſides their own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wit, are ſtill more refined in the Schools of the Philoſophers: The ſecond are ſuch as are pleaſed at ſome ſhowe and appearance, who have not yet been able to quit the inclinations, which the World has
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106061:66"/>inſpired them with for theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, and who cannot forbear the having ſome eſteem for the pomp of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Pagan</hi> Ceremonies. The firſt ſort have thought that Chriſtian Religion would be much more conſidered, if it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain many Miſteries, which were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and difficult to comprehend; Judging, that as plainneſs cauſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, obſcurity would gain it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and veneration. They have <hi>formed</hi> difficulties upon all the points of Religion, to exerciſe their wits on, and to ſhow their skill and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which they bring with them from the Schools. They have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed doubts to ariſe from the things which are moſt eaſy. In a word, they have changed the Chriſtian School, into a School of Branglings and Diſputes. Which heretofore cauſed a certain Perſon to ſay, that <hi>the Philoſophers had been the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106061:67"/>of the Heretiques.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other Spirits, who are for having ſome ſhow in Religion, fancy that if the Chriſtian Church, were but reduced into the ſimplicity which it had in its firſt riſe, it would have but a few Followers. They ſee that Men naturally do love that which pleaſes the Senſes, and which conveys devotion into the heart, by the Eyes and Eares. It is from this notion, that all theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral different Ceremonies are crept in amongſt us, which we ſee practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among Chriſtians. They have retained <hi>Jewdaiſme,</hi> nay more, they have brought in ſuch <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> as they have deemed moſt proper, to imprint, by outward objects, ſome inward Motives to Devotion and Zeal. They have imagined that they could with profit make uſe of thoſe things, which the others abuſed. They have ſuppoſed, that that was
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106061:67"/>the way to ſanctifie the profane Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the <hi>Egiptians,</hi> and bring back that to its true uſe, which nouriſhed the <hi>Pagan</hi> Superſtition.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, how ſpecious ſoever the Reaſons and Pretences are which one and the other alledg in their own favour. Theſe are they who have given the firſt ſtroke to the Peace and Union of the Church. For if at firſt, they had religiouſly kept themſelves to the ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Rules, which the Goſpel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes us; they had never ſoparated into ſo many Sects, as have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, concerning ſuch queſtions as the curioſity of Men has cauſed to be raiſed. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> tells us, that his Yoke is eaſy to bear. He invites all even to the very little Children to believe in Him; which he would not have done, if the Faith had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly brought with it all thoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruce Rules and Miſteries which are
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106061:68"/>propoſed to us now. The Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prures do preſent but very few Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, in compariſon of the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to Vertue, which are there made us. And the Goſpel is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us, but that we ſhould believe that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and that in believing it, we may have life through his Name: <hi>John</hi> 20. To be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Baptized, It is ſufficient to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve from the Heart, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the Son of God: <hi>Acts</hi> 8. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reduces all his preaching to this only Point. That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> foretold by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that he was to be crucified, and riſe again from the dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. The ſame reports that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his knowledg is to know <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> and Him Crucified. The Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> requires not more of him that would approach neer to God, but the knowledg of two things; that there is one God,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106061:68"/>and that he is the Rewarder of thoſe who ſeek after Him. And St. <hi>James</hi> makes pure Religion, and blameleſs before God, to conſiſt in viſiting the Widow and Fatherleſs in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and in keeping themſelves from being defiled by this World. As if they would have ſaid, that the Principal deſign of Religion is, to bend all ones ſtudy to Sanctity, to Purity, and to Charity. The Creed of the Apoſtles, contains whatſoever is Eſſential in the Rules of Chriſtian Religion. And what that teaches us is ſufficient for the Conſolation of our Souls, and to induce us to a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life. Let us but examine all the Apologies of the firſt Chriſtians, written on purpoſe to diſcover their Opinions in Religion: They juſtifie all that which I aſſert. They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend but a very few Articles of Faith, as concerning the exiſtence of God, the Incarnation of our Lord,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106061:69"/>his Birth, Life, Death and Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Hence it is that they have defended themſelves from the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations which were brought againſt them, that they have reſiſted the ſtrongeſt temptations, and ſuſtained with courage the moſt violent Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions. If they had continued in that courſe, and had not conſulted the Schools of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> concerning the Rules of Religion, there had been no change made; then had there been no ſeparation in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. If the wit of Man had not been ambitious to mix his own, with the Divine Oracles, the Church would have ſtill been in its innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and in its purity: Such are all theſe new Opinions, which being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the evidence of truth, have ſeparated Mens Spirits, and cauſed this unhappy Diviſion.</p>
               <p>And as to this matter of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and of the outward ſhow of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106061:69"/>the Church; If they had conſidered them as ſimple Ornaments, which are nothing of the Eſſence of Religion; If they had not multiplyed them to ſo vaſt a number. If herein, they had kept up themſelves to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of their practice in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church. They had had no occaſion for any conteſts concerning theſe things, and every one might have eaſily found wherewithall to be ſatisfied. But ſince they have without meaſure, increaſed the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ceremonies; So that they have not left Chriſtians the Liberty of making the leaſt ſtep in Religion, without upholding it by ſome Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; They have put things to a tryal; Every one has pretended to have a right to ſpeak his ſence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which has made many to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and given occaſion of Diviſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:106061:70"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>That many do make uſe of Religion, to ſerve their particular Interests, and the advantages of a temporrl Life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe greateſt Evil which Reigns in Society, is, that a right di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction has never been made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſolid and true goods, and thoſe which have no foundation, but in the imagination of Man. We of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten prefer a Worldly intereſt before all the advantages of the Soul, and the hopes of that which is to come. Sometimes alſo after a moſt wicked and deteſtable manner, there are thoſe who make Religion, and an appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Devotion, ſerve for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining or preſerving ſome temporal and paſſing good. Inſomuch, that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106061:70"/>as it is from this particular intereſt, which contentions do ordinarily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, it muſt not be thought ſtrange, if being mixt in Religion, it cauſes ſeparation and diviſion there. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is but the ſpecious pretext which theſe People make uſe of, for advancing their affairs, and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing their fortunes in the World. 'Tis no more to them than an acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to attain to their principal, which is their aggrandizing and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelves powerful. And ſince it is not the glory of God which they propoſe to themſelves in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, we muſt not wonder, if God permits Diſcord to ruine a deſign, the motives whereof are ſo vile and ſo ſhameful. When a Religion is once eſtabliſhed in an Eſtate, the moſt do not examine whither or no it be well founded in its Rules; and whether it contribute to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all. Every one conſults
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106061:71"/>whether the profeſſion which is made thereof, may be accomodated to the poſture of his own affairs, and to the ſubſiſtence of his Family. The moſt principal Perſons of the State think they ought to maintain it againſt all others, at what Price ſoever. They think, that if they ſhould leave to private Men a Liberty of examining it, there would happen a great deal of trouble by the contradiction of thoſe who might oppoſe it. So that it is not at all any Pious Motive, which incites them to maintain that Religion which bears the ſway, but an Intereſt meerly Politique and Worldly. It is not the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God's glory, and defence of the truth, which they propoſe to themſelves: 'Tis their own advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they endeavour to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage by the Rules of Humane Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and this Prudence ordinarily ſuggeſts to them, not to exerciſe any
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106061:71"/>but an outward Devotion for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of their Ends. Whence it comes to paſs that God (curſing this conduct) permits, in deſpight of all their prudence, ſome bold Spirits to ariſe up amongſt them, who freely diſcover their Opinions; daringly publiſh the defects of that Religion, which bears ſo much ſway, make themſelves heads of Factions, and ſow Diviſions not only in the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but likewiſe in the State. I leave it to thoſe who have but the leaſt inſight into the Hiſtory of our Times, to make proof of this truth, by examples known to every one.</p>
               <p>The Intereſts of private Perſons do not work with leſs power on their ſpirits, than the Intereſts of a State buſie the Politicians who go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern it: And their paſſions likewiſe do not contribute leſs to the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and diviſions in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106061:72"/>How many are there, who coming to eſtabliſh themſelves in a Country, where divers Religions are tolerated, do preſently queſtion which of theſe Religions they ought to follow; whereupon they conſult this kind of Prudence, which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them to find out that profeſſion which is the probableſt to turn beſt to accompt. If there be any Great Man in the State, and they expect ſome ſupport or protection from Him; They take ſpecial care not to throw themſelves into any commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which their Protector ſhall not approve of. They particularly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to engage themſelves in the Religion of the Prince, whom they are more afraid of offending, than their own Conſciences. Others there are likewiſe, who although they ſee one of theſe Communions leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the State than the other is, by reaſon of its weakneſs and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106061:72"/>ſmall number of Followers, will not yet forbear to liſt themſelves there, meerly for ſome carnal Intereſts; 'Tis very often ambition, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Rule, which carries them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they hope to acquire more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, in having ſome eminent employment in a ſimple Barge, than if they were thruſt amongſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Seamen in a great Fleet. They make a large preamble to thoſe of their Party, telling them a fine ſtory how they are diſintereſſed and diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged of all things that may receive a temptation, and might make them hope for any advantage in the world: They declare that they have prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Religion abandoned and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, before one wherein they might have had ſufficient profits, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancements; And if they obtain not ſpeedily what they aimed at, they let them know that they are powerfully ſolicited to forſake them, and that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106061:73"/>their falling off will cauſe a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Rent amongſt them. Theſe People draw falſe concluſions from their falſe Principles, as if ambition and ſelf-intereſt did not many times work by occult ways, and under falſe pretences; and as though Men travelled not ſometimes to a vain glory by back ways, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their affairs in the World, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the mask of Zeal and Devotion; and theſe are chiefly ſuch as make the greateſt noiſe in their Society: Theſe are they who are the moſt Zealous in appearance; They who declaim moſt highly againſt ſuch as do not approve of their Party. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe are they who contribute moſt of all to Diviſion, to ſtrengthen, in favour of it, a Body whereof they would make themſelves Maſters. So that in the choice of a Religion, Men do ordinarily take that which is cleare contrary to the Precept of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106061:73"/>
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> They do not above all things ſeek the Kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof: But they ſeek every other thing before that which is moſt important. We ſhould not only prefer God's inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and Glory before our temporal advantages, but we ought not to deſire thoſe very advantages, but for the Glory of God and our own Salvation; and leave the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal thereof to the providence of him, who takes particular care of the leaſt Creatures. Theſe People on the contrary are very inquiſitive to know in what way of Worſhip they may live moſt commodiouſly with all their Family; afterwards they informe themſelves, and ſeek about on all ſides by what means ſoever to widen their Conſciences, that ſo they may favour, without trouble or remorſe, the Paſſion which rules them.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:106061:74"/>
               <p>After that, Judge if theſe Men (ſo diſpoſed) are not in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, blindly to follow thoſe, to whom they have joyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: If they who move not, but by ſuch ill Principles, are not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being made ſubject to what-ſoever ſhall be deſired of them, to advance their own So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and Ruine others. Hence it is that all thoſe dangerous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices does ariſe, which are in Religion, like a thick Cloud, that obſcures the Underſtanding. This it is, that hinders us from diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Truth, and from work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Motives of a ſincere Charity. After once a particular Intereſt hath taken place in our Spirits, it excludes all others from thence. It cannot ſuffer any concurrent; And, if we be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times obliged to take in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106061:74"/>Intereſts, it is but upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that they ſhall be ſubject to that which was firſt ſeated in our heart and affections.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:75"/>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:106061:75"/>
            <head>THE <hi>RE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITING</hi> OF CHRISTIANITY</head>
            <head>PART III. <hi>Of the proper means to Reunite all Chriſtians into one ſole Communion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the ill Means which has been made uſe of hitherto, for putting a Remedy to the Evil of this Diviſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter having conſidered the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this Evil, whereof we
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106061:76"/>have undertaken the Cure: After having made known the extent, the depth, and the conſequences; found out the cauſes, and traced them up to their very ſource; Order directs us to come to the remedies which are requiſite to the curing thereof. But before we propoſe them, it will not be at all from the purpoſe, to ſay ſomething of thoſe which hitherto have been unprofitably employed therein. And I do not wonder that we could never yet ſee any ſucceſs of whatſoever has been done, for ſtopping the courſe of ſo great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order. Men have always built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this wrong Foundation; That this Evil was of it ſelf incurable, and that therefore they could only ſtudy how they might ſtop the courſe of its moſt pernicious ſymptoms. They have believed it was but like going about to ſave a ſick Perſons Life, that was given over by the Phyſicians.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106061:76"/>They never thought of a means of reducing all the Societies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians into One. They have imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the difference of their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions was too great, and concerning matters too important, ever to bring it about, that all the ends ſhould be made to meet together. They have fancied that the Alienation of Mens minds was too inveterate, the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices too many, the intereſts too diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerent and too deeply rooted, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably to hope that either one or other, would make the firſt advance towards ſuch an agreement. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that every one has ſuppoſed it was enough for him to ſtrenthen himſelf in his Opinions, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh them by good Reaſons, and to weaken thoſe which are oppoſite to them, that they may draw to their ſides ſuch as ſhould reject them.</p>
               <p>It is on this Foundation, that all thoſe have hitherto worked, to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106061:77"/>whom God has beſtowed any great Talents, and who have had any Name in Divinity. All theſe diſputes, conferences, and volumes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies are not employed, but to this end, <hi>viz.</hi> to maintain the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which they have embraced, and to induce others to the receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. But in this, all theſe great inconveniences have never been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered; That thoſe very ſame who write, and who diſpute with ſo much heat and ſubtilty, are many times us much byaſſed as others, and their paſſions are as violent as thoſe in vulgar Perſons; That oft-times they alledg on both ſides very ſpecious Reaſons, and ſuch as cauſe new dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties to ariſe, of which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily clear themſelves; That all private Perſons have not the time, and conveniences requiſite, to be able to read over theſe kind of Writings, and hear theſe Diſputes;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106061:77"/>That of thoſe likewiſe who are in a condition to apply themſelves here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: There are but few who bring not ſome ſtrong conceipts in favour of thoſe Opinions, which they have followed before. Inſomuch that on theſe occaſions, we ſee but few, who give not all the applauſe to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of their Communion, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem not the others as conſuted, and bafled Teachers. So as I dare boldly ſay, that all theſe Writings, and all theſe Diſputes being far off from producing any good effects, ſhall but cauſe the minds of Men to be more wedded to their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and remove them further off from any ſincere Reconciliation. Let us ſay then with Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Epiſt.</hi> 122. That this Evil has more need of tears and lamenting, than of large Writings and great Volumes. Many times the Diſcourſes which have been us'd for obliging the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106061:78"/>party to follow another profeſſion, have ſerved but ſtill more to animate the Parties, and fortiſie them in their ſeparation.</p>
               <p>Therefore many ſeeing the ſmall ſucceſs of this Remedy, which has been endeavoured, have judged that they ought to change their Method, and work the Cure after another way. For effecting of which, they have diſtinguiſhed between ſuch So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of Chriſtians, whom they have believed to have groſs and dangerous Opinions; and others whom they ſuppoſed not to lye in ſo great Errour. As to the firſt, they have given them over as ſick Perſons, in ſo deplorable a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that their Diſeaſe is ſtronger than all Remedies. But they have made ſome ſteps towards the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the latter; they have offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them a hand of Reconciliation, and made them hope to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106061:78"/>in certain terms and expreſſions, whereon they ſhould agree. This is it, that all thoſe have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, who have hitherto applyed themſelves to the Reuniting of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks and Proteſtants. This is the way which they have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, who would have agreed the <hi>Lutherans</hi> with the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> and theſe again with the <hi>Arminians,</hi> and others who are gone out of their Communion. And yet after a world of trouble, and writings compoſed on this Subject, theſe deſigns have proved abortive, and theſe eſſayes unprofitable. For not to ſay any thing of the diſtinction which they make between pernicious Doctrines, and thoſe which are not ſo, (which is only contriv'd by their own ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereby they are already pre-engaged.) Is it not true, (as I have obſerved in the Preface,) that they are particular intereſts that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106061:79"/>have ſlipt in, and diverted the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, from a deſign, where another End was purſu'd than his Glory? As alſo that they have rather endeavoured herein to lull a ſleep, and give ſome kind of preſent eaſe to this Evil, than to cure it perfectly by any effectual Remedy. There has been made a certain mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Doctrines, and a compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things which can never be incorporated together, whereas they ought to have laboured to purifie Chriſtian Religion, and ſeparate it from that mixture of all ſtrange things, and bring it back to its firſt ſimplicity. Indeed they have failed herein, for want of looking up to the Fountain Head of this Evil, to diſcover what firſt made this ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among Chriſtians, of what communion ſoever they are. We ought therefore, ſince it is ſo, to find out a means how to propound to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106061:79"/>all Chriſtians in general, ſomething wherewith to ſatisfie them in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertures, which ſhall be made them, and cauſe them all to underſtand the Intereſt which they have to reunite themſelves in one and the ſame Principle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſhort,</hi> Some there are who have fancied, that Councils and General Aſſemblies might put a good period to this Evil, by their Authority and great Learning, but many times In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and prejudicate Opinions raign as well in theſe Aſſemblies, as amongſt the particular Perſons which compoſe them. For we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſee that theſe kind of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies make Mens ſpirits more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in their firſt ſentiments, and cauſe a leſs diſpoſition to an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We ſee beſides that theſe ſame Aſſemblies are very ſeldome formed, but under the Authority
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106061:80"/>of one of the Sects of Chriſtians, and that whatſoever is propoſed therein, is to fortifie them the more againſt others, and to fix them more and more in their firſt Opinions. This is that which has cauſed many abſolutely to reject all Aſſemblies of this kind, and has been the ground of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaying, that, <hi>Every General Council begets a Warre.</hi> Therefore for the right management of this Deſigne, all Chriſtians generally ſhould agree together upon all things which regard their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good; they ſhould all work upon the ſame Principle, and if they convene any Aſſembly for the attaining to ſo good an end; no Chriſtian Society ſhould be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prevail by its Authority, and power over the reſt: But all ſhould have the Liberty of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106061:80"/>their Opinions, to be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards determined by that which ſhall be for the common good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:106061:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. The firſt meanes. <hi>To lay aſide all prejudices againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to throw off all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Intereſts, that ſo nothing may be propoſed by us, but the Glory of God, and the Salvation of Souls.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have already ſhown, that there is nothing ruines more the Peace of the Church, than the Intereſt of particular perſons. That the greateſt obſtruction to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union, is our prejudice againſt other Societies, which in time ſtrengthens our preconceived Opinions. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what we ſhould do <hi>out of hand</hi> for the ſucceſsfull carrying on of this deſign, is, to caſt off all particular
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:106061:81"/>Intereſts, and all theſe prejudices. I mean not to own any but the true and lawful Intereſts, that all ſhould meet in one point, which is that of the glory of God, our own Salvation, and the good of thoſe with whom we deſire to be rejoined. And it is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requiſite, to lay aſide all thoſe prepoſſeſſions of Spirit, which may render us leſs inclinable to thoſe propoſitions of peace, that may be offered us. And I am perſwaded that were we free from ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engagements and prejudices, we ſhould favourably hearken to all overtures of reconciliation which ſhould be made us.</p>
               <p>As for the lawful Intereſts which I ſpeak of, &amp; are fit to be propoſed in this affair, they are ſuch as have no regard to any imaginary good, but are real, ſolid, and eſſential to Man. Alſo this ſame good is never ſeparated from the Intereſts of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106061:82"/>Glory of God, and the eſtabliſhment of truth. I exclude therefore out of the rank of right motives, which ſhould guide us in the ſearch of the true Chriſtianity: Firſt of all, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever has relation to the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and commodities of the preſent life. I put into this number them who thurſt after honours, riches, pleaſures, and whatſoever is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of any carnal deſire. Hither I alſo refer whatſoever contributes to the ſatisfaction of our inordinate paſſions, where they revolt from the obedience which they owe to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. I am certain that this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will be approved by every one. There is no Man who will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that things ſo different can never be match'd together. All will agree in the general Theſis, that as there is no Union betwixt Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: So we cannot joyn the ſtrict holineſs of the Coeleſtial Doctrine,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:106061:82"/>with the impure liberty of our Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. But there often ſlip in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain particular Intereſts, the which being more ſecret, and ſuch as do paſs more dexterouſly under the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of ſome ſpecious pretence, are not yet leſs prejudicial to the peace of the Church. Such is an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and turbulent Zeal in Men, which becauſe it ſeems exempt from thoſe other groſs intereſts, of which we have been ſpeaking, they appear as though they had only piety for their rule and meaſure in all their Motions. 'Tis for the moſt part obſerved, that this Zeal is nothing, but a meer obſtinacy and ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs, which can never depart from that which it hath once receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This Intereſt which ordinarily ariſes, either from ignorance, from an inveterate cuſtome, or from ſome other ſuch motive, engages us ſo much the more in diviſion, by how
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:106061:83"/>much it is covered with the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Devotion. And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that many of thoſe who read this part, if they conſider it with themſelves, will confeſs that I touch upon a String, which though ſmall, yet is not at all the leſs intelligible. To th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe apparent Intereſts, I joyn thoſe of ſome particular Perſons, who being willing to paſs for ſworn Enemies of inconſtancy, and levity, perſevere in the profeſſion which they have followed from their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy. They call it raſhneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency, to depart ſo readily from thoſe Tenets in Religion, which they firſt embraced; and they hold, that before they can do it, they muſt be fully convinced of the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof, and the evident peril which they incur by retaining them. Wherefore ſo long as they find any appearance, or probability, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe it ſtands with their pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:106061:83"/>to abandon them. I have known ſome of theſe, who have been ſo ſtrongly prepoſſeſſed with this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that they could not forbear ſhowing a leſs eſteem of ſuch as had embraced their ſentiments, than of thoſe who had ſtill perſiſted in the contrary party. To theſe ſpecious Intereſts, I muſt yet add one more; and that is a diſpoſition of Spirit, which we find many to have, who being entred into a Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it would be a ſhameful thing, ſhould it be ſaid of them, that they have examined their Religion too late. They imagin, that ſhould they confeſs they have continu'd in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to theſe Years, and that they had never in all this time perceived the weakneſs of their former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, People would take all the reſt to be want of diſcretion, irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and impiety. To flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves herein, they endeavour to make
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:106061:84"/>ſome kind of ſuperficial conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they have made of the Rules of their Sect, paſs for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and profound ſearch into the reaſons of their belief. After which, they maintain it with confidence, as not at all doubting, but that they are in the right way. There are ſome others, who are directly oppoſite to thoſe, of whom I have now been ſpeaking; Theſe are ſuch as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, and bid defiance to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they have formerly believed; who imagine that all new Opinions, which are propoſed to them, are far better than thoſe wherein they have been brought up. They are like thoſe of whom an Ancient ſays, that out of fear, they make all their prudence conſiſt in following every other councel, but their own. So theſe timorous Spirits in Religion, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the firſt Opinions which are propounded to them, and prefer al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:106061:84"/>new Doctrines, before thoſe which were received before. We ſhould therefore check all thoſe bad inclinations, which nature, educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, age, ignorance, and example may give us: For whilſt we liſten to any one of theſe voices, we ſhall be but in an ill condition to entertain the propoſitions of an Agreement. All theſe propoſitions will at the firſt inſtant appear ſuſpicious to us, and at laſt we ſhall reject them abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely.</p>
               <p>After this, to do well, we muſt caſt away from us all theſe unhappy prejudices againſt others, and high conceipts of our own Opinions, which cauſe almoſt all the difor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that ordinarily happen in the Church. Theſe are ſo many clouds which darken the underſtanding, and hinder Men from ſeeing diſtinctly the Objects, upon which they ſhould make their judgment. They are a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:106061:85"/>Glaſſes, which repreſent to us all that we look on, the clear contrary way, as dyed with their own colour. How would you have a Man, whoſe ſpirit is filled with an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ideas, upon which he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fixed, be able, after this, to make room for thoſe which are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to them, although they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally more effectual to his ſalvation? They muſt be all excluded to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them together without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, they muſt be ſeen naked, and that held, which ſhall be judged moſt reaſonable. There has been not long ſince propoſed, in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, an excellent way of right diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, and keeping a direct courſe for ſearching out the truth. They ſay, that for effecting of this, all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceived Opinions, and prepoſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſpirit muſt be abſolutely caſt away. That then they muſt not take up any, but the moſt plain notions,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:106061:85"/>and ſuch Propoſitions as cannot be quarreled at by any who have the leaſt uſe of reaſon. Why then can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not we imitate this manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure in Religion? Can we not for a while ſet aſide all theſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which we defended heretofore with ſo much eagerneſs and heat, to examine them afterwards more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and without any paſſion, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſely to our common Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which is the Holy Scripture? Can we notwithout any <hi>prejudice</hi> look upon the Foundations of Religion, which all they who are called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do generally acknowledg, and the Principles which they all agree upon? Would it not be an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible means to know with a diſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted mind, how we ſhould advance in a right way, and how we might build upon a ſolid Foundation, and ſuch as ſhould be approved by every one?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:106061:86"/>My deſire therefore is, that theſe prejudices and ſtrong fancies of our own Opinions may be quitted, which bind us in a Religion, rather by falſe appearances, than by Judgment and Reaſon. Hence is it that ſome boaſt of their antiquity, the ſucceſſion of their Paſtors, the Government of their Communion, their temporal advantages, the riches, ſplendour, and magnificence of their Temples, and Ornaments. Hence is it that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory in their plainneſs, and the ſmallneſs of their number, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which is made of them in ſociety, and other things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which the World cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. Laſtly, there are others extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the knowledge and talents of their Doctors: the ſanctity, auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and mortifications of their Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, the Zeal of their Martyrs, and other exteriour things, and acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals to Religion. For it may ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:106061:86"/>that all theſe may meet in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, which are not approved of by thoſe, who boaſt of them, as ſo many titles in their favour. There are likewiſe ſome, who, although they ſeem not to regard any thing, but Religion, by putting away what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not eſſential to it, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear falling into prejudices and errours of dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Such are thoſe who believe that their Doctrine is to be prefered before others, by reaſon of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the learned Men which defend it, the Arguments with which they appear to be ſupported, and the great motions of Virtue which they ſeem to inſpire. They conſider not that all theſe things may be alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Societies, whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine they do not approve: That at leaſt the Followers of the reſt might make a like Judgment of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; ſeeing the friends of each of
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:106061:87"/>them are prepoſſeſſed with reaſons in favour of their own. We ought therefore for a while to caſt off all theſe particular Sentiments, which form the divers Societies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; in ſuch manner, that it ſhould not be the Authority of any one amongſt them, that ſhould bear ſway over the reſt; but the ſole infallible Rule of truth, which is the Word of God: For, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is univerſally received by all Chriſtians, there ought to be no difficulty, in ſubmitting to whatſoever it clearly teaches us. This being ſo, how can we doubt of the bleſſing of GOD, upon ſuch an Enterprize, ſince we have no other thing for our Intereſt, than his Glory; for our Rule, than his Word; and for our End, than our Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:106061:87"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. The Second meanes. <hi>That we ſhould not have for our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, more than one known and generally approved Rule, for all Chriſtians to walk by.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen we ſay, that for the attaining to a perfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union, we muſt be free from all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate prejudices; I mean not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the eſtabliſhing of an indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and leaving Mens minds in a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence, without knowing what to reſolve on. 'Tis only to render ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unſure foundations, ſuſpected, and to ſearch out for one which may be firm and ſolid, and which the whole World ſhould agree to be ſo.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:106061:88"/>Now there is but one of this nature, and that is the Sacred Word of God, which he hath given us by the Miniſtry of his Servants. He hath given it us expreſly to be the Rule, both of our Faith, and all our Actions, in what concerns his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And it is too evident, that all do not agree on other matters. All do not hold that the Church is infallible. All do not acknowledg, that there is an unwritten Word, which is of as much Authority, as that which is in the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles. All do not pretend that we muſt be guided by that, which the Holy Ghoſt ſhall dictate, by his ſecret motions in the Hearts of the Faithful. But all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, without exception, hold, that God ſpeaking to us in his Holy Word, muſt be hearkened to, and that we muſt obey him without any reſtriction. If, beſides this, there
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:106061:88"/>ſhall be found any Confeſſion of Faith, which has been drawn from the Holy Scriptures, and drawn in ſuch a manner, as that it retains a Doctrine ſo pure, that all Chriſtians may ſecurely receive it: It may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well be joyned with this Word, delivered to us from God. And ſuch, in my Opinion, is the Apoſtles Creed: there never having been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, as I have ever heard, any Chriſtian who denyed to entertain it, as being an Extract, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium of the Goſpel. And, if that had been well practiſed, which the Council of <hi>Chalceden</hi> enjoyned, of not adding any other Doctrine to this Symbole, we had never ſeen Chriſtianity divided into ſo many Sects, as at preſent it is.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not here undertake to prove the Divinity of this Holy Writing; as having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow only to do with Chriſtians, who all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:106061:89"/>it. This is a thing that I may poſſibly handle in the third Treatiſe, which I have promiſed to publiſh, in the Preface to this Piece. For my deſign therein is, to let all People of the World ſee the advantages of the Chriſtian Religion above others: I ſhall alſo there endeavour to give to every one, a means of looking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it without theſe obſtinate preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, which would certainly make us reject any Doctrine, now tending ſoever to our Salvation. At the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, me thinks, for the working with ſucceſs towards a good Reunion, we ſhould riſe to a Principle wherein we all agree; It would be a very good ſtep towards a Peace, when we ſhould find a Subject wherein we could all Unite. For, according to that Univerſal Maxime, Things which agree in a Third, agree alſo together. If therefore we all receive the Word of God, as our Soveraign
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:106061:89"/>Rule; might we not probably hope that we may be Re-united in other things, which are but dependances on that; eſpecially if after we have caſt away from us all our paſſions, and prejudicate Opinions, we bring only with us a true Zeal, and an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Charity? Moreover, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Doctrine contained in theſe Holy Scriptures is Divine, that it is true, that it is infallible, and that it is perfectly Holy, we ſhal without doubt conclude, that it is our Soveraign Rule: That it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to us what we ſhould all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and receive for our Salvation. And as this word expreſly forbids us to add, diminiſh, or alter any thing in the Doctrine, which it lays open to us, we ſhould look upon all other Doctrines received in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Society of Chriſtians, us very ſuſpicious: We ſhould not receive them, tili after a careful examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:106061:90"/>of them, and upon ſure conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how ſpecious ſoever the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences were, under which they would make them paſs to us. Although they ſhould give them to us meerly as Explications, Illuſtrations, and conſequences drawn from this word: we ſhould however look upon them, but as Eſſays of Man's wit, whoſe infirmity appears in all his actions. All his meditations, his applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his reaſoning his Humility, his Prayers, and his Faſtings, cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but that there will remain ſtill great weakneſſes of Fleſh, which wil render him lyable to contempt and errour. There is none but God only who is able to declare to Us the things which are of God; becauſe there is none but God who knows God; as an excellent Author of our times has very well expreſſed. What Men ſay of Him, is but babbling. Whatſoever they bring thither of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:106061:90"/>their own, is but weak and doubtful. <hi>De divinis, etiam vera dicere, pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſum eſt.</hi> We muſt go to the very Truth it ſelf, and aſcend up to the Fountain Head. We muſt ſuſpect all the Waters which have not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through this Channel, although they appear never ſo excellent.</p>
               <p>Oh that we had but made known with a little diligence amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, the value of this important Principle, as we have ſown the ſeeds of Diviſion, that we had avoided unprofitable queſtions and diſputes; And had made Chriſtian Religion eaſy and intelligible, as carefully as Particular Doctors have taken upon them the liberty of expounding this Scripture. Every one giving it the ſence which his Genius, or rather his capricious Fancy, or Intereſt ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to him: Every one having drawn the conſequences from it,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:106061:91"/>which muſt favour his inclinations: Nay. and without ſticking there, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one has endeavoured to give to theſe conſequences, an authority e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to that of the Original, from whence he pretends to have drawn them. In this very manner have we ſeen Diſputes and Contentions ariſe, alſo Hereſies, Schiſmes, Diviſions, and different Communions. Every Society has made his particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which they pretend ought to be of as great authority, as the very Creed of the Apoſtles themſelves. And thus, as this Practice has ſtrengthened it ſelf in the Church, after the ſame rate alſo has Diviſion been ſtrengthened and augmented. It is therefore abſolutely neceſſary for the eſtabliſhing a good Peace in the Church, to reject all Inventions of Men, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to lend an Ear, but to God only, ſpeaking in his Word. It is thus, that the great Perſons
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:106061:91"/>have practiſed, who lived in the moſt pure Age of the Church. They have ever confined their mindes to the Holy Scriptures, as to the only Foundation of our Faith, and of our Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:106061:92"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The Third means. <hi>Rightly to diſtinguiſh between the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which the Holy Scriptures propound to be believed by true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and what regards only the outward Government of the Church, and its Ceremonies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Sacred Word, which we have ſaid, is the only Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Churches ſubſiſtence, and of the Union of its Members, offers Us three ſorts of things to be learnt by Us. It declares to Us; Firſt, what we are to believe, for the Peace of our Conſciences, and for obtaining Salvation, and Eternal life. It teaches us next, what relates to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:106061:92"/>the Government of the Church, in the Exerciſe of its Diſcipline, and in the outward Practice of its Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. And Laſtly, it gives Us ſaving Precepts, which ſerve for the Direction of our Lives, and Manners; Not only to be the outward Guide of our Actions, and of our Words: But alſo of our Affections, Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and moſt ſecret Motions of our Souls. This diſtinction being well eſtabliſhed, and all its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers truly conſidered: We ſhall find that in the right management hereof, there will be no occaſion of quarrelling, unleſs it be about the Rules propoſed to our Faith. For as to what concerns the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Virtue, they are ſo clearly laid open in the Holy Scriptures, that in them there can be no ground for Controverſie. All Chriſtians know that God will be moſt highly loved and adored. All agree that
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:106061:93"/>we muſt honour Father and Mother, according to the Commandment of God. All accord in this Point, that the Law of God forbids Murder, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, Lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All acknowledg that theſe Laws are not meerly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed to Rule the outward Form of Men in Society: But that they oblige us to conform the moſt ſecret thoughts and inclinations of our hearts, to the Purity and Sanctity which they command. After this we need not any other Rule, than that Abridgment of the Law, which the Son of God has reduced to theſe two admirable Precepts; To love God with all our affections; and our Neighbour as our ſelves. The Obſervation which might be made from hence, would Rule, as every one may perceive, all our actions; Inſomuch that no Perſon could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire any thing more for the living holily, and juſtly. I know very well
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:106061:93"/>that there have been certain Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors formerly amongſt Chriſtians, who by their interpretations, have gone aſide from the ſtrict obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Laws; But they have not only wanted the approbation of others, as well of their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as ſtrangers: But alſo they themſelves have always made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of acquieſcing, as others, in theſe ſacred and inviolable Rules. They did not pretend to weaken them by their interpretations: they only ſooth'd Men's conſciences with a favourable ſence, which they give to the circumſtances of particular actions. Behold here one of the principal Articles of Faith; Nay, I dare ſay, the moſt important, and wherein conſiſts the very Eſſence of Religion, which can give no cauſe of Diviſion.</p>
               <p>As to the Rules which the Holy Scriptures afford us for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:106061:94"/>of the Church, relating to its Diſcipline, and to its Ceremonies: 'Tis a ſtrange thing that they ſhould have ſo often given occaſion of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, and been the cauſe of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and diviſion. If the Holy Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men had punctually preſcribed, and ordered every thing that ought to be done in this matter; we ſhould be obliged indiſpenſibly to obſerve them. And we ſhould have reaſon to ſeparate our ſelves from thoſe, who did depart from them. But ſeeing that this ſacred Word is contented to give us, for this purpoſe, certain general Precepts: For St. <hi>Paul</hi> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells us, that <hi>Theſe things muſt be done with Order and Decency.</hi> Liberty is given without doubt to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to diſpoſe of theſe, according as they ſhall think convenient, having regard to the circumſtances of Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of Times, and of Perſons, in keeping always within the Bounds
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:106061:94"/>of Decency, and Order. For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, the Scripture has thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it ſelf hereupon: The nature of the thing ſeems palpably to lead us to the ſame. There is no Body, who does not put a great difference between that which is eſſential to a thing, and that which is meerly acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental. All acknowledg, it is on the preſervation of the firſt, that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of its ſubject does abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depend; that it can be very well maintained without the ſecond, and that alſo more conveniently. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that we ſhould act quite other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the firſt, than we ſhould for the other. So to preſerve health, or to recover it, though we ſtrictly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Diet which is obſolutely requiſite, we can freely and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice, change the Reliſhes and Tinctures, which we give to the Fod, and to the Medicines.</p>
               <p>This being once well ſetled, every
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:106061:95"/>one ſees how unreaſonable a thing it would be, to ſeparate about the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of any difference, which might happen in outward matters, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentals to Religion, ſhould there be any Schiſme in the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Order which is to be amongſt its Governours? Muſt this Holy Union be broken, becauſe ſome would have the Church be govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Biſhops, and others would have an equality amongſt its Paſtors? Muſt we, becauſe of ſome diverſity in the Habits of thoſe who officiate in the Church, break the knot which ſhould tye all Chriſtians together? Is it juſt that for the Ornaments of the Temples, the poſtures wherein private Perſons ſhould be, during the acts of Devotion, and other ſuch Ceremonies, the peace of the Church ſhould be ruined, and the Unity of its Members? Has not the Primitive Church made it well appear, that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:106061:95"/>there was no ſuch matter of ſcruple, when it freely changed the practice, according as the times and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons required it? Did not <hi>Tertullian,</hi> one of its principal Doctors, teach us, that the Rule of Faith continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firm and conſtant; other things which regard the Diſcipline, do ſometimes ſuffer alterations and changes? Were the Temples always ſet out in this magnificence, which they are in at preſent among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? Were Faſtings always after the ſame manner obſerved? Were the Garments of Miniſters of the Church always in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me mode? Have they at all times, and in all places received the holy Euchariſt after the ſame faſhion, as to their outward Geſtures? Has there not always been great diverſity in the practice of theſe things, and can we not ſtill be able to ſuffer it, without being forced to ſeparate, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:106061:96"/>the Church, as we do at this preſent time?</p>
               <p>I confeſs that in certain Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſome things may fall out to be practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which would directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the Fundamental Points of Religion. But it would be eaſy to give a Remedy to this Evil, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Order which I ſhall propoſe. We ſhould in this caſe, look back to the very Precept it ſelf, upon which we ſhould all agree together. For if we all accord in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Doctrine, we ſhall find no great difficulty to accord, or at leaſt to maintain a charitable judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the uſe of the Ceremony. If we were once but well Reunited together, in the Opinions which we ſhould have of the Doctrine, I am aſſured, that we ſhould bear with one another, in things which are not of that importance. If we joyned
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:106061:96"/>in the main eſſential matters, the neceſſaries would not eaſily ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us.</p>
               <p>Behold then, how this happy means of Peace muſt be ordered. It is by eſtabliſhing immediately, with great care, the bounds which are to be given to theſe two things; That is, Firſt, that a right diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be made between what ſerves for the outward conduct of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of true Believers, and the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and internal concern of a good Chriſtian: Next, that we labour and ſeek out by all the ways imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, how we may be Reunited in what reſpects the eſſence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. But for that which reſpects the outward Government, and the Ceremonies of the Church, ſome liberty ſhould be given to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Societies of Chriſtians. Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in regard muſt be had to the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Places and Climates, where
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:106061:97"/>they dwell, which often create more diſguſt to one ſort of Government, than to another. Alſo there ſhould be conſidered the diverſity of their Politique Government, which may imprint ſome ſtamps of its Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter upon that of the Church. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, We ſhould likewiſe have in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, what theſe Societies may have practiſed hitherto, with ſucceſs in this reſpect, and leave them the entire diſpoſal thereof, after having repreſented to them what ſhall be judged more proſitable, and more commodious for them. This diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity muſt not alter the peace of the Church; It is not juſt, that agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in the eſſential Points, we ſhould break the bonds of our amity, for things which are not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential. How many Brothers are there, who although they be of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent employments, yet for all this leave not off their living together as
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:106061:97"/>Brothers, and making up one and the ſame Family. I would therefore have an accomodation made herein, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cuſtomes, and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Places, in which they live. That in all parts, where they ſhould inhabit and ſojourn, they might be ſubject to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſtians, which ſhould be there eſtabliſhed, without condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or blaming other Cuſtomes. That we ſhould rather believe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably, that every one has followed herein, the Order which has been ſuppoſed to be moſt convenient, and moſt requiſite to Salvation; ſeeing that ſtill the Principal which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in few Articles, continues firm. Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> was accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.33. Endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pleaſe, and accommodate all matters, without ſeeking after par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular conveniencies, but only the Salvation of many. And when he
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:106061:98"/>ſaw any who would be contentious in theſe things; He only anſwered them thus, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>We have no ſuch Cuſtome:</hi> Showing that it argues a contentious ſpirit, and an enemy to the Peace of the Church, to be unwilling to follow Order and Cuſtome in things of this nature. We ſhould always ſix here, that we ought not, barely upon account of humane Inſtitutions, to ſeparate one from another, ſeeing we break with thoſe, who embrace the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which we do, clearly taught us in the Word of God, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that they have not the ſame practice with us in the outward part of Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:106061:98"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. The Fourth meanes. <hi>To diſtinguiſh between that which the Scripture propoſes to us to believe, as Doctrine of Salvation; and that which it delivers to us, as Hiſtories of things which have happened; and that which it reports to us, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of things to come.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOllowing the diſtinction made, in the foregoing Chapter, of all the things which are propoſed to us in the Holy Scripture: We muſt firſt examine what it declares to us, as truths, which the true Believer ought to receive by Faith. Theſe are not all of a like nature; and muſt alſo be carefully diſtinguiſhed,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:106061:99"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:106061:99"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:106061:100"/>to take away likewiſe all cauſe of contention among Chriſtians. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, therefore, they may all be brought under theſe three Heads. As firſt, the Myſteries of Religion, which ought to be believed, for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Conſcience at reſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing its Salvation. Secondly, the Hiſtorical Narrations which the Scripture makes us, of many things that have happened, as well in the Diſpoſition of the Order of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, as in the Government of the Church, under the Old and New Covenant. Thirdly, the predictions there made, as of things which muſt happen, and whereof we ſee not yet the accompliſhment. This being concluded, we ſhould generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerve as unqueſtionable truths, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God has revealed to us in his Word. Wherein there are many things which ſhould not, neither can they give any matter of contention,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:106061:100"/>much leſs of Diviſion. As for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Hiſtorical Relations of the Holy Scriptures are ſuch, that all Chriſtians generally receive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m, as certain and indubitable, and if there be any diverſity of Opimons upon any difficulties of Chronology: That ſhould not cauſe a ſeparation in the Church; The Opinions may be left to the Liberty of particular Perſons, to follow therein, what they ſhall judge moſt probable. I ſay the ſame of interpretations, which may be given to ſome obſcure paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, which ſhould not cauſe any Diviſion, be the diverſity never ſo great, which is there met with. There is but one ſole occaſion for allowing it, and that is, when a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular interpretation overthrowes ſome one of the Fundamental Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, or that they would make it to paſs, as iſſued out from the very mouth of God himſelf. For all theſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:106061:101"/>interpretations are but ſo many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of Man's wit, which may fail<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Inſomuch that we ſhould leave to every one the liberty of examining them, to receive them afterwards, or to reject them without prejudice to Salvation, and without breaking the Union, which is had with thoſe of contrary Opinions.</p>
               <p>As to what concerns ſuture pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, neither ought theſe to be the ſubject of any Diviſion. It may ſuffice, we are all in general perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that whatſoever has been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, in the Holy Scriptures, ſhall have its accompliſhment, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the obſtacles which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſere. 'Tis ſufficient to believe, that the firſt Cauſe abſolutely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of ſecond cauſes, will bring about its deſigns, in deſpite of all reſiſtance of the Creatures. This hinders not from advancing our thoughts higher, ſearching into the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:106061:101"/>ſenſe of the propheſie, and making our conjectures of the times of its execution. We ſhould in this give Liberty to certain particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, eſpecially when theſe kinds of Meditations may contribute to the Conſolation of true Believers, and to excite them more to ſanctity. It is in this, I make that happineſs conſiſt, which the Book of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calypſe attributes to thoſe who read it carefully, and underſtand it. But he who would apply himſelf to this ſtudy, muſt not do it, but with great precautions. Here it is, that much ſtrictneſs muſt be obſerved, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally not the leaſt ſtirring be made but from a principle of deep humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. He muſt on all occaſions di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt himſelf, but more in this, than any other. For although theſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles be not conceived in ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous termes, as thoſe of the <hi>Pagans</hi> were; yet are they propoſed in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:106061:102"/>and dark expreſſions; They are ſuch hidden myſteries, and ſo profound, that they can ſcarcely be fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>omed. When predictions are accompliſhed, they change their nature, and become Hiſtories eaſy to be underſtood: But before the Event, they muſt be looked upon with that profound reſpect, as cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes naturally a ſilence. But yet if any think they have eſpy'd ſome light, they may utter their thought with modeſty; And ſhould rather propoſe it as a conjecture, than as a certain Doctrine. For truly there is nothing ſo dangerous, nor ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the peace of the Church, as the deſire of making paſs our ſence upon things foretold, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant truths. There needs but a forc'd Opinion of theſe Propheſies, to ſtir up a whole Nation to tumult, to diſturb the peace of States, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the Unity which ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:106061:102"/>Chriſtians. The Examples of this, are as well known as they are Dreadful to Conſider. There might ſome kind of Parallel be made between this Reflection, and thoſe dangerous obſtinate Opinions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have already made mention, and which muſt be entirely caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, to attain to a perfect intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:106061:103"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. Fifth Advice. <hi>Touching the Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion, which we muſt believe, as being Revealed in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and concerning the distincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which muſt be made of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter having conſidered metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically, of what the Word of God teaches us, touching the Rites, Ceremonies, and outward Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church, as alſo the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and Propheſies which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains; After having ſhown that in all theſe things there ſhould be no matter of Contention among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: I have nothing leſs to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, but what concerns the Rules,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:106061:103"/>comprehending the Holy Myſteries of Chriſtianity, which Believers ſhould own, and receive for their Salvation. And becauſe it is a moſt important matter, it muſt be clearly open'd, and explained, to remove whatſoever might give any occaſion of Contention, and procure herein, as well as in the reſt, a Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Chriſtian Societies.</p>
               <p>I cannot now abſolutely diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the Diſtinction, which all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors make in this matter, and of which I have already ſpoken. If I acknowledge there be in Religion ſome important Precepts, eſſential, fundamental, and neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; I acknowledg therein alſo others leſs important, which might be let alone, as where ſome Errour may ſlip in; Yet this may be done without prejudicing our Salvation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Peace of Conſciences, and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of the Church. But what
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:106061:104"/>I cannot approve of in this, is the Application which theſe Doctors make of this diſtinction, to their Cauſe. They commonly fall, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter, into the ſame faults which have been obſerved; Namely their prejudicate Opinions, and particular Intereſts, which for the moſt part bear ſway in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they make of what is Fundamental, and what is not. So that they would oblige all, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into their Communion, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in Humane Doctrines, as if they were ſo many Fundamental Points. They oblige Men alſo to Reject the Doctrines which agree not with theirs, as if they tended to overthrow the Foundations of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, although they may not be ſo prejudicial, as they would make them believe. For who has Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of fixing that which is Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, and diſtinguiſhing it from
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:106061:104"/>that which is not? If it were left to the diſpoſition of Men, every Society would do therein according to their prejudicate Opinions, which they have been poſſeſſed with, formerly admitted. Whence is it therefore that we ſhould take the Foundation of this diſtinction, but from the Mouſh of God Himſelf, ſpeaking to Us in his Holy Word?</p>
               <p>True it is, we find not any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Holy Scriptures, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in formal termes, which are the Fundamental Doctrines, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them from others. But the nature of the thing tells us, we may eſtabliſh this diſtinction, by the very Word of God. For if all Chriſtians receive, as unqueſtionable truths, all that which has been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to Us in the Word of God: If they all acknowledg that it would be an unpardonable crime, but to call in doubt any of theſe Sacred
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:106061:105"/>Oracles: (ſeeing it would be to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Him of falſhood, who is truth it ſelf.) They muſt by conſequence own, that whatſoever is clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to Us in the Word of God, and is alſo received by a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is a Fundamental Point of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. They muſt acquieſce in this Doctrine, as being immediately iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out from God, or elſe utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Chriſtianity. Whereas if there be Doctrines which have not been ſo clearly revealed to Us, they give occaſion to the Doctors, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe their Judgment, and give place to different Sences. We have likewiſe the liberty of examining theſe divers Opinions. We may compare them together, to retain that which we ſhall judg moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Analogy of Faith. We may ſearch out that which ſhall agree beſt with the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Points, which gives moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:106061:105"/>to the Soul, and affords the greateſt Motives to Piety. But we muſt not put theſe laſt truths in the ſame rank with the firſt, nor muſt we oblige Chriſtians to acquieſce there, in the ſame degree of Faith. As to the firſt, we ſhould receive them as ſo many Oracles delivered from the Mouth of God, without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of humane infirmity; whereas the ſecond, which have paſſed through the Diſcourſes of Men, may have been altered by the weakneſs of their Judgment. They may be tainted with the defects and imperfections of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wit. And theſe are thoſe truths or rather thoſe Doctrines, which I do not allow to be Fundamental. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we ſhould give to Man, and to Reaſon, an Authority, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to none, but to God alone, and his Word. And to the end we may clear this matter by Examples which may make it both known and
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:106061:106"/>underſtood by every one; It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that theſe are Fundamental Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in Chriſtianity; Viz. <hi>That there is One God:</hi> That he hath ſent his only Son into the World, <hi>That whoſoever believes in Him may have Eternal Life.</hi> That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> dyed for our Sins, and aroſe again for our Juſtification. That He ſhall come in his Glory, <hi>to judg both the quick and the dead,</hi> and ſuch other truths, as all Chriſtians admit of, as being moſt diſtinctly and plainly taught us in the Holy Scriptures. But as for thoſe Doctrines, which determine the Order of the Eternal Decrees of God; that tell us punctually what is the Object of Predeſtination; that Expound how the two Natures are united, in the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> that comprehend and fadome the Myſtery of the Trinity; that pretend to diſcover the means, by which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> operates in the hearts of
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:106061:106"/>the Faithful, and other things of the like Nature. I maintain that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Learned Men ſhould ſay never ſo many excellent things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe matters, and what they ſay might be approved, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judged reaſonable.) They muſt not nevertheleſs be made to paſs, as of equal authority with the truths which are clearly revealed to us in God's Word. They ought indeed to be received but in ſuch manner, as that we ſhould be all ready to quit, and renounce them, in caſe any one ſhould make us ſee ſome error therein; Otherwiſe it is but to make way for Diviſion: Since every Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor will make his particular Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to paſs for ſo many Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Truths: And will reject all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as Errors which utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Salvation. The adverſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will not be leſs Zealous in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their contrary Opinions,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:106061:107"/>which will be followed by a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeparation and diviſion. Here it is that we ſhould value the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Prove all things, and hold faſt that which is Good.</hi> Here it is alſo, that the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Apoſtle might take place; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>That there is but one ſole Foundation of Chriſtian Religion, which is Jeſus Christ: That Man might build upon it Gold, Silver, precious Stones, Wood, Hay, or Stubble: But that every Man's work ſhall be made manifest; For it ſhall be tryed by Fire: which will conſume the evil works, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the workers may be preſerved.</hi> Let us in the next place, hear what the excellent Author of that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Imitation of Chriſt, ſays. <hi>What will it avail thee, though thou canſt diſpute concerning the depth of the Myſtery of the Trinity, if, in the mean time, thou ſhalt be destitute of the Grace of Humility, which may make
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:106061:107"/>Thee acceptable to the Trinity? The profound Diſcourſes of Divines, make not a Man more Holy, and more Juſt. I had rather feel the true effects of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, than know how to give a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This diſtinction being ſetled, the ready way will be open to us, by which we may attain to a perfect Reunion of all Chriſtians, in one Confeſſion of Faith. In the firſt place, I ſuppoſe that we muſt have a ſtrong Faith, having ſuppreſſed all particular Intereſts, which have no regard, but to temporal things; That we muſt for ſome time have caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all thoſe prejudicate Opinions, which are ſo many bars and hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of agreement; After this, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that we ſhould adhere with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out varying, to the certain and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Rule, which is the Voice of God, ſpeaking to us in his Word: That according to this Word, we
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:106061:108"/>bear one with the other in the divers practice of its Eccleſiaſtical Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and in the different uſe of its Ceremonies. That we ſhould not look upon theſe outward things, but as accidentals to Religion, and which ought not to be eſtabliſhed, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the general Rule of Order and Decency. I next require, that we all reſt in the Truth of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Hiſtories, leaving a Liberty to learned Men, of declaring their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions upon the difficulties, which are therein met with, to follow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſtraint, that Party which ſhall be judged moſt reaſonable; That we read not the Propheſies and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions contained in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, but with Humility, without determining any thing, as by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, upon their ſence, and the times of their accompliſhment; That we carefully diſtinguiſh between the Doctrines, ſo clearly eſtabliſhed in
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:106061:108"/>the Word of God, that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are obliged to receive them: And thoſe which have need, for their enlightning, of the Labour, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of Men, to clear them; That we admit not of any other, than the firſt for Fundamentals, and unvariable: And that as to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we may diſpence with our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving them, without prejudice to our Salvation, which ought not to depend, but on the firſt; Or, if we do receive them, it ſhould be but as humane Opinions, which we judg moſt probable, which nevertheleſs we are ready to forſake, ſo ſoon as we ſhall know them not to be well grounded. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I undertake that all this may be done, without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Peace and Unity, which we ſhould entertain with thoſe, who have different Opinions upon theſe Queſtions, on condition that they receive them not, but after the ſame
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:106061:109"/>manner which we receive ours; That is to ſay, as Humane Doctrines which may have their uſe, but which ſhould not engage Us, as thoſe which are iſſued from God, without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Humane Infirmity. After that, I believe there is no body, who does not judg that, being ſo well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, all Chriſtians generally ſhall live in a Perfect Unity, which is the Mark whereto we ſhould all aime.</p>
               <p>And to juſtifie that, what I here lay down, is not without Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that we may attain to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Chriſtianity, without engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Labyrinth of all theſe knotty Queſtions of the Schooles. Suppoſe it ſhould ſo happen, that ſome Chriſtian might be driven by a Tempeſt into the Country, about the Straights of <hi>Magellan,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parts, where the Inhabitants never heard ſpeak of our Myſteries.
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:106061:109"/>Farther, I would not have this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian know any but the firſt, and moſt plain Rudiments of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, contained in his <hi>CREED.</hi> I ſuppoſe him only to be perſwaded of theſe truths: That there is One God, who hath created the Heaven and the Earth; That he requires of us Perfect Holineſs; That we have violated his Ordinances, which has rendred us unworthy of his mercies; That nevertheleſs he has invited us ſtill to Repentance, and to Salvation; That He has ſent for this Purpoſe, Him, whom He Himſelf calls His Son; That this Son dyed for our Sins; That He is riſen again for our Juſtification; That He aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, and there makes Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for Us; And that if ſo be we are but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ully perſwaded of theſe truths; and will carefully ſtudy Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety towards God, and Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our Neighbours, we ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:106061:110"/>Eternal Happineſs. I ſuppoſe, that this Man teaches theſe things to this ſavage Nation, and that theſe People, who hitherto had been igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of all theſe truths, are taken with their beauty, and afterwards fully convinced of them, and will thereto conform their Lives: I ask if theſe People might not truly be called Chriſtians, and whether or no they were not in the ready way to Salvation. For my part, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make any difficulty to believe it, and paſſing further on, I ſhall ſay, that I ſhould eſteem them happier, if they continued in theſe Principles, than if we ſhould come to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them with all theſe critical Queſtions, with which we are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily entertained. <hi>John Moquet,</hi> in the Third Book of his Travels, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates a Hiſtory, which confirms this truth. A poor Chriſtian Woman being a Slave in one of the Principal
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:106061:110"/>Families of <hi>Morocco,</hi> taught the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion to the Maſter of the Houſe's Daughter; The Slave, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, was not able to give Her any, but the moſt General Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, according to the capacity of a Perſon of that Sex, and of that condition; Nevertheleſs this Noble Maid, new born to the Faith, was ſo throughly convinced of theſe Chriſtian truths, that ſhe quickly ſuffered Martyrdome for the defence of them, and that too with an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roique Virtue. Therefore as I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge but one ſole way, which God offers to all Men, for their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Salvation: So I conclude, that all thoſe who ſhall hold faſt to theſe Principles, ſo plain, and ſo few in Number, and live agreeably to them, will undoubtedly obtain Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:106061:111"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>What Ways muſt be followed, to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Execution of this Deſign.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS it is not enough for the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Diſeaſe, to be inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Remedy, which is proper for it, but we muſt alſo know its uſe, to apply it to purpoſe, and with ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: So it is not ſufficient that we know what will be a ſaving means to Reunite all Chriſtians in one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith: But we muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how this means muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to produce its effect; ſeeing great difficulties and obſtacles may be found in the practice, which thwart the Execution thereof. There might be alledged the remoteneſs of many, who are called by the Name
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:106061:111"/>of Chriſtians, whom it would be almoſt impoſſible to bring together, for concurring to ſo happy a Work. There might be produc'd the great Diverſity of Opinions, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; The Intereſts of Princes and States; The engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of whole Nations; The aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and animoſities, which are ſtrengthened by time. There might be alſo added the temporal advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, which thoſe who have any Eccleſiaſtical charges will be hardly perſwaded to part with, and as many other things, which may ariſe in the ſpirit of every one. All theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations might make this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition paſs for an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery and Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary project: At the beſt it might be ſaid to be a fair Idea, but very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to put in execution, which, like <hi>Plato</hi>'s Republique, is in the rank of things, which are more to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired than hoped for.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:106061:112"/>To which I may, in the firſt place, ſay, that if there ſhould be no other end propoſed herein, than this, of Labouring for the Glory of God, and the Peace of his Church, it might be hoped that he would ſecond with his Grace, ſo laudable a Deſign. It is to attend his Work, it is to eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his Raign in the World, it is to build up his Houſe. What? will he refuſe the ſuccours of his Grace, to thoſe who ſhall have no other aim, but his proper Intereſts? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we ſhall meet with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, which we cannot remedy upon the ſuddain, we ſhould not for that be diſcouraged, but expect from the Goodneſs of God, the ſucceſs of ſo pious an enterprize. It muſt not be thought ſtrange, if at preſent, God has left Chriſtians as deſtitute of the Graces, which he ſhowered down in the firſt times of Chriſtianity. His Spirit is not to be found among
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:106061:112"/>Tempeſts, and amidſt Whirlwinds: How? ſhould it be among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, divided into ſo many Sects, and animated with the Spirit of Diviſion, which raigns by paſſion and violenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> So ſoon as Charity is awakened, we ſhall then labour for the common Peace: That Spirit which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the firſt Diſciples, who were met together with one accord, in one place, will inſpire us in ſuch manner, that this great deſign will go forwards beyond all our hopes.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, ſeeing that God does not forbid us the endeavouring to make his Glory ſhine, with this ſmall ſtock of Prudence, which we have received from his Grace. I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we might happily proceed after this order in our deſign. It would be neceſſary, with all ſpeed to cauſe to be diſperſed, Writings of this Tenor, in divers Languages, and ſend them into all Places, where there
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:106061:113"/>ſhall be any Chriſtians; of what profeſſion ſoever they be. This would ſerve to undeceive an infinite number of prepoſſeſſed Spirits, and make them hope for the ſucceſs of an enterprize, which hitherto has been ſuppoſed impoſſible to finiſh. This would waken in divers places, many private Perſons, who would have an inclination to peace, and on whom God had powred his Grace, proper for contributing to ſo good an end. I am aſſured that they would be raviſhed to have ſo favourable an occaſion of working for the common good of Chriſtendom. They would certainly be aſtoniſhed at the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that they ſhould have been ſo long time without making a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this buſineſs, and without taking it by its true Meaſures. They would bleſs God for having opened ſo fair a Port, to enter into ſo great a Calm, after ſo many Tempeſts.
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:106061:113"/>They would ſutably qualify them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for the attaining to ſo deſirable an end. They would labour with all their induſtry, to bring thither thoſe of their Communion; and altogether would ſtrive to ſuſpend for a while their Judgments in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Articles, until by common conſent all that ſhould be regulated, which was requiſite to ſo happy a deſign.</p>
               <p>Beſides the writings which ſhould be employed to this end; Familiar converſations, and particular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes would much contribute thereunto. It is thus that we might do; and that we ought mutually to lend our aſſiſtance, for the clearing of theſe matters. We ought always to have in Proſpect, the Glory of God, and the Peace of his Church; and this ſhould be our principal buſineſs. There is not any thing, which oftner puts a ſtop to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:106061:114"/>of our greateſt deſigns, than the want of frequent unmasking, and laying them open. For the well-ordering of them, this muſt be often attempted, and all the difficulties by little and little removed, which ſhall occur therein. We are all generally more curious, to entertain our ſelves in converſe about any other thing, rather than that which is moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. The ſubjects moſt ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily fallen upon, in thoſe companies which are eſteemed to be the moſt regular, are full of vanity, if not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Newes of what paſſes in the World; Affairs of State; Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome difficult paſſage of the ancient Authors; Some queſtions of the Mathematicks, or of Phyſicks, and things of this nature, are the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary entertainment of theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous companies, which we ſo much admire. If any one ſhould propoſe ſuch a ſubject as this, which I treat
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:106061:114"/>of, either it is coldly received, or paſſed over lightly, to go to ſome other, which may give more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant reliſh to the company, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accomodated to the humours of the Age. And yet what more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſubject is there of our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than that which regards the general good of all Chriſtians? Let us bleſs the happy moment, wherein we have been brought to the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of this generous deſign, and contribute our endeavour towards its good ſucceſs; if we can let our ſelves be vanquiſhed by this Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation!</p>
               <p>Moreover it would be convenient, that all thoſe who have found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves perſwaded of the truth and advantage of this Propoſition, ſhould employ their greateſt care in advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the execution of it. If in traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, Men expoſe themſelves to ſo many perils, to tranſport their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:106061:115"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="193" facs="tcp:106061:115"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:106061:116"/>from one Country to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in hopes of ſome ſmall profit; Shall we ſit ſtill without communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the moſt precious Treaſure, and greateſt advantage which can arrive to Society? It is not here to be ſeared, that the number of thoſe who ſhall be ſharers in this good, will diminiſh the Portion of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſon: On the contrary, the increaſe of this number, will aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Satisfaction and Joy of thoſe, who make a part thereof: As thoſe that follow Armes, rejoyce to ſee their ſide grow ſtronger, and at the ſame time conceive thereat both Hopes and Joy. For, if we act in this Affair, but for the glory of God, the good of his Church, and our own Salvation, as we have even now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, the more true Believers we ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reunited together, to promote this end, the more Joy ſhall we have and the more ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:106061:116"/>But if private Perſons are obliged to contribute to ſo glorious an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize: I believe that thoſe who have any employment in the Church, in whatſoever Society it be, ought to be aſſiſtant therein, by a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar engagement. Their profeſſion calls them to it, their charge obliges them to it, and the Lights which they pretend to have above the Vulgar, ought only to guide them this way. They are as well reſponſible for the Souls of others, as for their own. They ſhould not propoſe any other Intereſts, than thoſe which are joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Intereſts of their Maſter; and his glory only ought to adorn theirs. If they uſe it otherwiſe, they are bad Servants, and Stewards of the Talents, which have been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them. But if they once ſtrive with Zeal, to promote this great Work, beſides their own comfort, the ſucceſs of it will make them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:106061:117"/>and more aſſur'd. People have commonly their Eyes on them, to follow their ſteps, and imitate their Examples; So that they draw after them, whole Troopes, Societies, Communities, and Sects, as it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices Him to gain the Officers of an Army, who would make Himſelf Maſter of all the Souldiers.</p>
               <p>But eſpecially, I make account, that thoſe who are able to give the greateſt ſtroke on this occaſion, are Princes, and all thoſe who have the Government of States, and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Publique Affairs. They can maintain with their Authority all theſe Reaſons, which ſhall be employed in this noble enterprize: And their power will be very effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, for making the Exhortations of others valued. It is not, that I mean this Affair ſhould be plainly carried on by the force and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Men. The underſtanding muſt
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:106061:117"/>herein be cleared, to gain over the Heart and the Affections, which is better done by reaſoning, than threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and by the force of Arguments, than by that of Armes. But ſince there may be ſome particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo wedded to their old Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that for their Worldly Intereſts, they would reject the good, which would be procured for them; It would be fit to hinder theſe People, by a Superiour Authority, from croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo happy a Deſign. If for Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſome Clergy-men, of any Community whatſoever, could not reſolve to quit their temporal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, which are of more weight with them, than the Publique Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: The authority of Princes, and Magiſtrates, would ſerve very well to reduce them to that which was Reaſon and Juſtice. There would alſo herein be this advantage expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, from thoſe who have the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:106061:118"/>in their Hands; namely, that by the Correſpondence and Alliance, which they have together, they might make this good, Univerſal to all Chriſtians. They might likewiſe Joyn their Forces, for repreſſing the boldneſs of Infidels and all Enemies to the Name of Chriſtians, who would oppoſe themſelves to ſo holy a Reſolution. Laſtly, they might maintain againſt all others, thoſe who would enter into this Holy Communion; But foraſmuch as this is one of the moſt powerful means, to attain to this end, and which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves more important conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I reſerve it to a particular Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, if this firſt Work ſtill be favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably entertain'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:106061:118"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Anſwers to the Objections, and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties which may be formed againſt this Deſign.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere can be no advantage pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, which meets not with its Difficulties; We cannot fetch Gold out of a Mine, but with much trouble; The Earth is not made fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, but when it is digged and plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great care: and the ſucceſs of the moſt admirable enter prizes is not obtained, but by ſurmounting with induſtry, all the obſtacles which are met with, in the execution of them. And yet this trouble we have in attaining th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe moſt excellent goods, is that which contributes much to their glory. It is a poor
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:106061:119"/>common Vertue which findes no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in its operations; The praiſe of Heroick Virtue conſiſts in the conquering of great difficulties. So that this project would be leſs admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable than it is, if it could be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without pain, and if the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof were eaſy. But what ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections may be made to this, and difficulties met with herein; will be altogether ſuch, as that we ſhall be eaſily able to Anſwer the One, and Remedy the other.</p>
               <p>Some will preſently ſay, That to attempt this, is, in a manner to go about to hinder an effect, which muſt neceſſarily happen. That it is, as if one ſhould undertake to ſtop the courſe of the Stars, and hinder the Revolution of the Seaſons. That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles have foretold there ſhould be Hereſies, Diſſentions, and Schiſmes in the Chriſtian Church. That this is
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:106061:119"/>permitted by the Providence of God, to make evident the Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of his Faithful Servants: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that it would be to ſtrive againſt the Eternal Decrees, and Rules appointed in the Counſel of God, to endeavour to prevent the diviſion or diſſention among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But for ſatisfying this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, beſides what has been ſaid upon this Point, at the beginning of this Treatiſe. There is but one thing to conſider, which is, that this Prediction is not only grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Decree of God, for the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things which ſhould happen in his Church; but upon an effect of the evil diſpoſition of the Spirits of Men, which is cauſe of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union. And that hinders Us not from labouring to remedy this cauſe, and put a ſtop to theſe deplorable effects. So that what <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> has foretold us of the Fire which he
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:106061:120"/>was come to kindle in the Earth, by the Preaching of his Goſpel, hinders not his Servants from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ng, with great affection, to extinguiſh it, and to ſtay the great burning which this Flame might cauſe; Moreover, if it were ſo, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> out, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it has been foretold: Yet it does not import thus much, that it ſhould abide continually. Is it not enough, that it has taken place for ſo many Ages? Is it not time to ſtop its Courſe, and ſee an end of it? So will the Propheſie have had its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment in our Fathers days, and we ſhall, in ours, enjoy the calm, after all theſe Tempeſts. Let us add hereunto, that this very word, which foretells us theſe Diviſions, makes us alſo hope for an eſtate of Peace, and Quiet in the Church. It makes times of refreſhment, and eaſe, to ſucceed all theſe great diſturbances; and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us that there ſhall be ſuch a
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:106061:120"/>firm Peace in the Earth, that we ſhall ſee thoſe Creatures, which are the greateſt Enemies one to the other, that is to ſay, thoſe Spirits wherein is the moſt contrariety, dwell, and unite together. Who knows, but that we may live to enjoy thoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py times? Who knows, but that in our days, we may ſee this general Peace among all Chriſtians? And I durſt promiſe, that by the aſſiſtance and bounty of God, This ſhall come to paſs, if our Sins do not put a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to it, and our particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts more ſway us, than the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good of Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>It muſt be ſaid in the ſecond place that this Deſign of bringing all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to acknowledg, but ſo ſmall a Number of Heads in Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, approved by every one, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and to the Practice of the Primitive Chriſtians. Thoſe, who
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:106061:121"/>diſpute ſo ſtrongly againſt the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours which aroſe in their times; Thoſe who condemned with ſo much indignation, all who did not conform to the Holy Doctrine, which they received from the Lord; Is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny likelihood that they would have hearkened to theſe Propoſitions of beating with one another, and a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable condeſcending in theſe Points of Religion? Would St. <hi>Paul</hi> have liſtened to ſuch an accommodation, who writ with ſo much ſharpneſs againſt the <hi>Galatians,</hi> who had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered themſelves to be ſeduced by certain falſe Teachers: Would St. <hi>John,</hi> who refuſed to have any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with Heretiques, have appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of this Overture? To which I anſwer, that what perſwaded theſe Holy Men, to act on this manner, was, that they regarded not ſo much the diverſity of Opinions, which they diſapproved, as the evil diſpoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:106061:121"/>of thoſe, who went about to eſtabliſh thoſe ill Opinions. They well ſaw that what theſe Perſons were about to contrive, was not out of a ſpirit of ſimplicity, and humility: They obſerv'd nothing in all their conduct, but particular Intereſts of Worldly honour, profit, authority, and rule, which all their endeavours carried them to. Theſe now are Motives, againſt which we can never make too much Zeal and Indignation appear. But we ſee, they dealt clearly other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with ſuch poor People, as had been ſeduced by theſe crafty Wits, than they did with theſe Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, theſe ſpirits of Lying. They <hi>treated</hi> thoſe with mildneſs, but theſe they condemned with ſeverity: They bare with the firſt, and had charity for them, but they had a Holy, and Juſt anger for the ſecond: They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſome Liberty to the former, but granted nothing to the Latter.
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:106061:122"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo how St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, is not afraid in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> queſtion of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our Bodies, (ſo important in R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,) o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing a great value on this holy and charitable bearing with one another. To this might be added that theſe Holy Men have been immediately inſpired by the ſpirit of God, to acknowledg, and make known to others theſe Heavenly truths. And this being ſo, they might condemn with boldneſs, and with knowledg of the Cauſe, thoſe who rejected the truth, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to them in the open Day; Whereas at preſent, we not having theſe Lights, and this Supernatural and Miraculous Aſſiſtance, are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to keep our ſelves ſtrictly to the expreſs termes of the Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Morcover, it might be Objected, that this Deſign is of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence:
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:106061:122"/>That it is to give to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one a liberty of having what Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he pleaſes; and alſo in matters of importance, ſuch as have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to divided Mens ſpirits; That it is to give an occaſion of falling inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly into an indifferency for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to favour, in ſome ſort, the contempt of all. Now, as this is a preſſing Objection, and able to drive from this deſign all good Souls, if it were well founded; I am confident that whoſoever ſhall have well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the Foundations which I have laid down, will find that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing further from my purpoſe, than this conſequence, which they would draw from it. This would be to make darkneſs ariſe from light, and as the Scripture ſays, to draw filthineſs from that which is pure, to imagine ſuch effects ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a cauſe ſo holy and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Can that which only tends to
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:106061:123"/>the Re-uniting of Chriſtians in the ſame Opinions, hurry them into im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and irreligion? Will that which brings Us back to the moſt plain, and moſt naked Doctrine of the Goſpel, cauſe an indifferency for Religion to ſpring from it? What then would this be, living without Religion, to be fully perſwaded, that there is a God, who hath created Heaven and Earth, who hath made Man kind, who puniſheth the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cheriſheth the Good? Is it to be without Religion, to believe firmly that we have no other means of getting out of that miſery, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Sins have caſt Us, but by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the promiſes which God has made Us, in his Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Is it to be indifferent in matters of Religion, to hold for certain, that there is no way to obtain Life and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happineſs, but by that of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and good Works? Is it to be
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:106061:123"/>impious, wholly to conſecrate our ſelves to the ſervice of God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rules which he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Us in his Word, under the colour, that there are but ſew Rules embraced; Yet however embraced, with an entire perſwaſion of their truth? I maintain, on the contrary, that all theſe defects of Piety, and all theſe inclinations to irreligion, do not proceed from any other cauſe, than this, that Religion has been o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged with too many curious and ſtrange Queſtions. I hold that it is this great number of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſcrupulous Obſervations of the externals of Religion, and ſuch other triſles, which have divided the minds of Men, and alienated the moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affections. For thoſe who are not penetrating enough to ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and reſolve all the difficulties which are met with in theſe kind of matters, ſuffer themſelves to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:106061:124"/>an indifferency. They never look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Religion, but as a Subject whereon the moſt ſubtil, and active Wits ſet themſelves awork. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if we did but once reduce Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, to the natural ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of its Rules, it would then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover all its graces and beauty, and would be lov'd by us all, becauſe it would have nothing in it, but what was lovely to our Eye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> There might be produced other difficulties, which might occur in the proſecution of this grand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. Some will ſay, that if it were a feaſible thing, it would have long ago come into the heads of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who would have tryed it; And if they did diſcover it, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome attempt in it, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they knew the execution of it to be impoſſible. That there are too many different Geniouſes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome, too many different Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:106061:124"/>to reconcile, too many Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and diſtruſts to ſurmount: That after we ſhall have begun to remedy the precedent evils, there will ariſe from this deſign other new ſubjects of contention and diſpute, and by conſequence of Diviſion. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance no body to this preſent has ever conſidered this affair, as I do: It may be, if they have made the ſame diſcovery, they have wanted application of ſpirit to form the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it, and clear the difficulties. For my part, I do not think the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties unconquerable: And I ſay once more, that would we <hi>engage</hi> in it with Zeal, and Religious motives, the affair would ſucceed happily, to the great good of all Chriſtendome. Theſe ſpirits would let themſelves be vanquiſhed by the motions of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and Charity. All theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſts would give place to that, of the Glory of our Soveraign.
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:106061:125"/>All theſe Jealouſies, and Diſtruſts would be ſmothered by an ardent Zeal, for the Service of God. And why ſhall I looſe the hopes of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in this generous Deſign? Did we not ſee, that at the Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at <hi>Poiſsy,</hi> in the Year 1561. The <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks and Proteſtants had almoſt agreed together about the termes, wherein the Article of the Communion ſhould be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Yet that is eſteemed the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt difference amongſt them. And had it not been for certain Doctors, who indeed, for their particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, broke off this accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it would then have been ſeen, that theſe two Grand Parties would have been reconciled together. Do we not know that at the Conference held at <hi>Marporg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> in the Year 1529. between <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inglius,</hi> they ſell into agreement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout certain expreſſions, almoſt in
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:106061:125"/>all the Points of Religion, and it was concluded, that as to thoſe whereon they could not likewiſe agree, they ſhould bear charitably one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that that ſhould not hinder the Reunion which was to be made. I know that afterwards it was croſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the ill diſpoſition of bad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. But, when all theſe particular Intereſts, and prejudicate Opinions, ſhall be removed, which have at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times croſſed all theſe fair de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, what ſhall hinder us from meeting in that Point, and true Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, now at laſt, wherein all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may be Reunited? Who ſhall hinder us in thoſe things, wherein it may be, we cannot eaſily be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, from uſing a charitable, and brotherly bearing with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And that ſo we may work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as well United Brethren, for the Glory of the Common Father of this great Chriſtian Family, whoſe
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:106061:126"/>Head, the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> cannot be divided? The greateſt rub is in the firſt ſteps, which muſt be made towards this Reunion, but this is no unconquerable difficulty.</p>
               <p>We read in the Relations of Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, made to the Eaſtern Countrys, that in <hi>Turky, Perſia, &amp;c.</hi> All the Chriſtians which are there met with, of whatſoever Sect they be, live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a perfect Unity, and give mutually all poſſible marks of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere friendſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Olearius</hi> obſerves, that in <hi>Perſia</hi> they make no difficulty of joyning together in their Devotions. And <hi>Peter de la Valle,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Gentleman, relates, (<hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 3.) that when an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſſadour arrived at <hi>Hiſpahan,</hi> a Conſultation was held, whether or no the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> which were there, ſhould go to Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit Him, and that by Joynt conſent
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:106061:126"/>they were of Opinion, that it was the common Intereſt, to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to that <hi>Mahometan</hi> Prince, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome difference that there was amongſt them in certain Points of Religion, yet that they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved together in a perfect correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. And he adds a very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Inſtance, <hi>VIZ.</hi> That in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> all the Chriſtians, both Catholiques and Heretiques (as his phraſe is) dwell together in ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and perfect an Unity, that once when he lived there, I know not upon what occaſion, the Jeſuits having fallen into ſome great trouble; The Ambaſſadours of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who otherwiſe are their mortal Enemies, (as he ſays) were the firſt, who ſpake in their favour, and made their buſineſs be diſpatched, with all the good ſucceſs which they could deſire. What hinders Us here in <hi>Europe,</hi> in the middeſt of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:106061:127"/>that we cannot do that, by a motive of Charity, which they in the <hi>Levant</hi> do by the Principle of the Intereſt of Trade, and civil Affairs, and that, we drawing again one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, ſhould not agree at laſt in the Fundamental Points, which may Unite Us altogether: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this Deſign ſhould not be ſo readily brought to perfection; Meditation would be very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and very conducing to it. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, who ſhall have taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of it, would draw much ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from it; They would be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſed, as to many of their precon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Opinions; They would finde themſelves diſcharged of a heavy Yoke; They would unmask Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and diſcover its beauteouſeſt Face, as being moſt pure, and moſt plain. They would love it, and dwell together in its profeſſion, with ſingular comfort. I
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:106061:127"/>ſhall alſo add this ſame, that if the Propoſition ſhould not ſucceed ſo happily, for all Chriſtians in general, it might take effect in many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular States of Europe. I mean a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe Chriſtians, where there are diverſities of Opinions and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions. Could we not, at leaſt in theſe places labour herein, for ſome good accommodation? And would not the Fruit which grows thence, be capable of inviting others to take a ſhare in it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:106061:128"/>
               <head>The Concluſion. <hi>The Profits and Advantages, which might be hoped for from this Deſign.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE muſt be very dim-ſighted, who cannot plainly ſee the ſignal advantages, which may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from ſo-excellent a Deſign. It would be an admirable means for advancing the Glory of God, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh his Doctrine, in the purity and ſimplicity which is natural to it. Men have been deſirous to ſupply by their prudence, the defects which they thought they had obſerved, in the conduct of providence. They thought that God had not in His Word explained Himſelf, neither clear enough, nor amply enough, to
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:106061:128"/>be underſtood, without aſſiſtance. Thence proceeded all theſe expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Paraphraſes, Commentaries, Queſtions and Diſputes, which have oppreſt, &amp; almoſt choaked the moſt excellent, and moſt holy Doctrine, that ever appeared in the World. If therefore we can but once rid her of this Burthen, ſhe will appear in all her luſter again, and eſtabliſh in its ancient purity the ſervice of Him, who is manifeſted by Her. Under the old Covenant, God rejected the Worſhip, which the moſt ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> offered him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that becauſe they had modell'd it according to their fancies, and had rather endeavoured the obſervance of theſe outward things, than the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and eſſence of true Piety. God refuſes his Graces to thoſe, who have no mind to receive them, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſimple and pure as they are: To mix them with ours, is abſolutely
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:106061:129"/>to ſpoil them. And now ſeeing we are ſo unhappy at this preſent, as not to enjoy the communication of the Graces of Heaven, nor that bleſſed commerce which the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had with God, who doubts but that this muſt needs come from hence, that we have quitted their ſimple and innocent carriage in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service? We have undertaken to ſerve Him after our manner, and we have endeavoured to know Him, only by ſuch Ideas, which our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prichious fancies have faſhion'd of Him; This has properly been the cloud, which has intercepted our ſight of Him; This, certainly, has been the Sin, which being the moſt capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of all, has made Him conceal Himſelf from us, and the provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which has obliged his Juſtice to chaſtize, by the deprivement of his Graces, thoſe who have neglected the ſimplicity of his Doctrine. We
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:106061:129"/>muſt therefore re-enter into that firſt eſtate of ſimplicity, humility, and charity, to recover that which we have loſt, that is to ſay, God and his Graces: And this is what we ſhould hope for, from the execution of this Deſign.</p>
               <p>The ſecond advantage which we may expect, is, that we ſhould find it much eaſier to extirpate Vice, and to procure the Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Society. We are driven to a neceſſity of certain Diſputes, and ſtrange Controverſies, whilſt we ſhould be rooting out the paſſions, which choak the Fruit of the Doctrin of the Goſpel. We make ſallies out upon the Enemy, whilſt Sedition mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſts us within. Let us caſt away theſe unprofitable Queſtions: We have enough to do, to make Anſwer to the Reproaches of our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. We ſhall never think of reforming our manners, whilſt we
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:106061:130"/>ſpend the chiefeſt of our time, in maintaining theſe impertinent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes. We ſhall not be able to defend our ſelves from ill examples, if we employ our Armes in vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of indifferent Opinions, which cannot ſo long be debated <hi>Pro,</hi> &amp; <hi>Con,</hi> without prejudice to Salvation: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſince this diverſity of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions deſtroys, as it hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, both Charity, which is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Chriſtian vertues, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which is the ſoul of them. The fire of this Diviſion muſt firſt be extinguiſhed, before we can proceed, with ſucceſs, towards the Correction of Manners and Reformation of Life. Therefore it is this, that all good Chriſtian Souls do ſigh after.</p>
               <p>We might have great reaſon to hope that the State would have alſo a conſiderable advantage by this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. People would become more tractable, and ſubmit with more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:106061:130"/>to the Orders of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, when they ſhould ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves united with them in the ſame Profeſſion. It has been lways obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that mens Affections have never been ſtraightly linked together, where their Minds have been divivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by different Opinions: Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all thoſe ſubtilties, which we cauſe to ariſe about Religion, do or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily make peoples ſpirits inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, proud, ſtanding upon puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio's, obſtinate, and by conſequence, more difficult to be brought to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and their Obedience. Every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man pretends to have a right of taking cogniſance of thoſe Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Matters, to inrerpoſe his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein, and then with great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency ro defend them. After this, in Affairs of State they will take the ſame liberty, which they gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in thoſe of Religion. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that if it be permitted them to
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:106061:131"/>controll the Opinions of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours in the Church, where the Service of God is; it ſhould likewiſe be free for them to examine the Conduct of thoſe who are ſet over them in State. Thus the Reunion which I propoſe, will be a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful means to hold every one in his Duty.</p>
               <p>All Princes of Chriſtendom would draw conſiderable advantages from this deſign, beſides the Obedience of their Subjects, of which I have now been ſpeaking. They might ſtrictly unite themſelves together; For theſe Jealouſies, theſe Diſtruſts and theſe Diviſions, which ordinaiily ariſe from diverſiry of Profeſſions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſolutely to ceaſe, all theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Intereſts, which ſeparate them, would unite in one, and the Fruit would be common to them all. This Intereſt would carry them on jointly to oppoſe themſelves to the
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:106061:131"/>Enemies of the Name of Chriſtian, and take over them all advantage, which reaſon &amp; juſtice could allow. Is it not a ſtrange thing that ſince the Roman Catholicks, the Proteſtants and the Greeks have ſo rent and torn each other; we ſee that the Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans have made ſo great a progreſs amongſt them, by reaſon of their Diviſions? If, when the Turks came to fix themſelves in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and then afterwards attacqued the State of the Venetians, all Chriſtendom with one accord had oppoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their deſigns; Had they reaped thoſe advantages; which now they have obtained over thoſe two States? Is it not a very aſtoniſhing, not to ſay a ſhameful, thing, that ſome neighbouring Countries to thoſe dreadful-Enemies of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, do think themſelves obliged to treat with them, and that alſo upon diſadvantagious Terms, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:106061:132"/>out of the Diſtruſts and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies which they have of other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? They ſhamefully make Peace with the Turks, to turn their Arms againſt the Chriſtians; eſteeming it to be running to that which is the moſt preſſing neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Thus the common Enemy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and gets much ground e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, by reaſon of our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. To ſtop this evil, I ſee no other more effectual remedy, than to haſten this Agreement of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, which (without doubt) will be followed by that of affections.</p>
               <p>The <hi>common</hi> People will find herein this ſatisfaction, that they ſhall no more be troubled in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, with ſo great a number of Queſtions, and diverſity of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, propoſed to them as neceſſary to Salvation. Hereby will be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from hence all thoſe Scruples of Conſcience, thoſe Troubles,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:106061:132"/>thoſe Alarms and thoſe Diſtruſts, ſo directly oppoſite to the Genius of Chriſtian Religion, and to the Peace which the Eternal Soh of God has procured for us. Thus the ſimple Artificers, the Labourers, and thoſe who are moſt unlearned and ignorant would be guided in the way of Salvation, and be led to the enjoyment of eternal Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Doctors, by this means, would not have any advantage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the people, in the Knowledge and practiſe of things neceſſary to Salvation. It might be ſaid, that hitherto there have been, as it were, two different Religions, in one and the ſame Religion: The firſt is of the learned and Scholars, the other that of the common People, Women and Children: Yet <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> never had a double Auditory, he never inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Phariſes and the Doctors of the Law otherwiſe than the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:106061:133"/>People: And when he choſe Succeſſors to ſupply his room, they were poor Fiſhermen, who had more concern in the inſtructing and ſaving of ſuch as were like them in condition, than boaſting their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty in the Diſputes of the Schools, and confounding ſuch as thought to have the advantage over others in arguing.</p>
               <p>I am alſo perſuaded, that thoſe particularly, who are employed in Eccleſiaſtical Charges, and called to teach others, will here find great advantage. They will no more tread upon thoſe Thorns, which heretofore they met with, in all thoſe critical and unprofitable Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions: They will have no more thoſe Diſtruſts and Alarms, which they gave themſelves, doubting if they were not in a wrong way, and if they miſled not others: They will not fear the encountring a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:106061:133"/>which is truer than that they profeſs. Let them ſay what they will, this thought oftentimes makes their hearts ake, who, amongſt them, have tender Conſciences. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing themſelves delivered from all thoſe unquietneſſes, they would acquit themſelves of their Charge with much more Joy. They would labour with pleaſure for the Advancement of the Glory of God. They would bend all their thoughts to ſtir up every one to a good life, and they themſelves would be Examples to others, of Vertue, Piety and Charity. 'Tis often ſeen, that amidſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions which the Doctors raiſe about ſome Niceties of Doctrinal Points, there is little or no Zeal for the Glory of God. They grow ſo paſſionate for the getting of ſome advantage in a Diſpute, until, at laſt, they let themſelves be maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:106061:134"/>and vanquiſhed by their own Paſſions. Many times ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies make us forget that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs that we ſhould have with our ſelves; and ſome ſtudy more how to ſpeak well, and diſpute well, than how to live well.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, who does not ſee, that if we bring this deſign about, it will prove an excellent means to draw to the Goſpell many people, who look not upon it now but with averſion and contempt. This Simplicity, this Beauty, and this Facility which is obſerved in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, together with the perfect Unity of the Profeſſors thereof, will be a powerful Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to attract to it, all theſe, who hitherto have rejected it: When they ſhall ſee that this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religion is not made to conſiſt meerly in Ceremonies, that is to ſay, in outward grimaces, which
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:106061:134"/>moſt commonly terrifie and keep off thoſe that are well inclined towards it, rather than invite them to follow it: When they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more hear talk of all thoſe cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and troubleſome Queſtions, which are riſen up in Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: When they ſhall obſerve no more particular intereſts predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in the Spirit of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: When they ſhall be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that there is nothing but the Love of God, Charity towards our Neighbour, and the deſire of living well, which inſpires them: Laſtly, when they ſhall ſee in the Faces of theſe Chriſtians the marks of true Peace and Comfort, which the Chriſtian poſſeſſes within: They muſt have deprived themſelves of all ſence of Vertue, they muſt have extinguiſhed utterly all ſparks of Reaſon, and turn ſworn enemies of their own good, if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:106061:135"/>not to enter into a Society which hath all theſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>I doubt not alſo but thoſe bleſſed Spirits who continually ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of God, will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the Advantages of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Union; for if they ſo much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt themſelves in the converſion of a poor ſinner, that they rejoyce and ſing aloud in the Quire of Glory, will they not make a ſolemn Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val in Heaven for the reuniting of all Chriſtians upon earth? I am alſo perſuaded, that God, ſeeing we all bend our Courſe toward him, with the ſame heart and the ſame affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, will certainly come to meet and receive us; He will embrace us in his mercies, and ſpeak to us in the motions of his loving kindneſs, eſpecially if <hi>we ſay</hi> to him with the Author of that Treatiſe of the Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſt, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 3. <hi>I am
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:106061:135"/>weary with hearing and reading ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things. It is in thee alone, O my God, that all is included which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or wiſh for. Let all Doctors hold their peace, let all Creatures keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in thy preſence, and be thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alone to ſpeak to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wiſh with all my heart, that all theſe conſiderations may make ſuch an impreſſion upon the ſpirits of all thoſe who ſhall read this Writing, that every one may afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, according to his power, to the advancement of this great work; and that God would favour, in ſuch manner, our attempts with his Grace, that we might ſuddainly ſee a happy ſucceſs therein to his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the good of all Chriſtians. And becauſe my voice is too weak to awaken them, and draw them out of the eſtate where I behold them now; I wiſh they would hear that of the great Apoſtle of the
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:106061:136"/>Gentiles, whoſe Voice and Stile all Chriſtians know. He calls to them thus, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Be ye kind one to another in love, endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace. There is but one body and one ſpirit, even as you are called to one hope of your vocation: There is but one Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, one God and Father of all, who is over all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> This great ſervant of God like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beſeeches them all, with words capable to work upon the hardeſt hearts, ſpeaking to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Chap. 2. <hi>If,</hi> ſays he, <hi>there be any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels of mercy, if any compaſſion; make my Joy compleat, that ye be of the ſame opinion, having the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, being of the ſame courage and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcing in the ſame thing. Neither let any thing be done amongſt you with
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:106061:136"/>ſtrife, or vain glory: But rather e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming one the other, in humility of ſpirit, more excellent than himſelf, not every one regarding his own particular intereſt, but that alſo which appertains to others. Let there be therefore, one mind in you, like that which was alſo in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To whom, with the Father, be Glory for ever and ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:137"/>
            <head>Theſe Books are Printed and Sold by <hi>William Gilbert,</hi> at the <hi>Half Moon</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>THe Annals of the Old and New Teſtament by <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Armagh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Danielis Sennerti opera omnia,</hi> 3. Tom. <hi>Venet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poeta Graeci Veteres Carminis Heroici Scriptores, qui extant, omnes.</hi> 2 Tom.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Biblia Graeca. Francoſurti.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Book of Martyrs by <hi>J. Fox</hi> 3 Vol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alexander de Ales.</hi> 4 Vol.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jani Alexandri Ferrarii Caenobitae Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtiniani Euclides Catholicus, ſive demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratio Romanae fidei ex primis, certis &amp; evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus
<pb facs="tcp:106061:137"/>Principiis, Mathematica methodo &amp; connexis continua ſeriv propoſitionibus deducta.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Regal Protomartyr, or the Memorial of the Martyrdom of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, in a Sermon preached upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, by <hi>John Allington</hi> Rector of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Learn to lie warm, or an Apology for that Proverb, It is good ſheltring under old Hedg: containing Reaſons where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a young Man ſhould marry an old Woman.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miltons</hi> Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> from the firſt traditional beginning to the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt.</item>
               <item>The Way to get Wealth, by <hi>Gervaſe Markham.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo.</head>
               <item>Diſcourſe of Evangelical Love, Church Peace and Unity.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Rogue, or the Witty Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, in four parts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hools</hi> Greek Teſtament.</item>
               <item>The laſt and now only compleat Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the neweſt and choiſeſt Songs and Poems that are now extant at Court,
<pb facs="tcp:106061:138"/>Theatres and elſewhere, with above for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty new Songs never before in Print, which are now added to this ſecond part of <hi>Wiſtminster</hi> Drollery.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Duodecimo.</head>
               <item>Hungarian Rebellion, an Hiſtorical Relation of the late wicked Practices of the three Counts, <hi>Nadaſti, Serini</hi> and <hi>Frangepani;</hi> tending to ſubvert the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of his preſent Imperial Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and introduce the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometan, with their Arraignment, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and manner, of Execution. By <hi>P. A</hi> Gent.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106061:138"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
